GOOD AFTERNOON AND WELCOME TO THE JUNE 30TH 2026 REGULAR
MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT MAY THERE BE A
ONE TIME THING EVERYONE WE DO HAVE AN APPROVED BOARD RULE
THAT THERE ARE NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF SUPPORT OR AGAINST
ANYONE. THANK YOU KINDLY.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL
MEMBERS ARE PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA
ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE
RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE
BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA ALUMNI COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE AND COLLEAGUES.
BEFORE WE GET INTO OUR MEETING SUPERVISOR FIELDER WHO HAS
RETURNED FROM HER EXTENDED LEAVE HAS ASKED THAT WE GRANT
HER PRIVILEGE OF THE FLOOR TO PROVIDE SOME REMARKS AND IF
THERE ARE NO OBJECTIONS AND I DON'T SEE ANY I THINK WE CAN
GIVE HER GRANT HER PRIVILEGE WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELD WAS PROVIDED PRIVILEGE OF THE FLOOR
. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
AND THANK YOU, COLLEAGUES. I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
GRACE IN EXTENDING A EXCUSE FOR MY ABSENCE FOR AN EXTENDED
LEAVE. IT'S NOT SOMETHING THAT I
WANTED TO DO BUT SOMETHING THAT MY DOCTOR RECOMMENDED AND I'M
VERY GLAD I DID TAKE THE TIME TO PROTECT MY MENTAL HEALTH.
IN THIS TIME I'VE HAD A STEADFAST TEAM IN AND JEN,
SHEILA AND SASHA, I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR DEDICATION
AND ALL THE HARD WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE TO ENSURE OUR
CONSTITUENTS CONTINUE TO BE SERVED IN DISTRICT NINE
AND MOVING OUR LEGISLATION FORWARD.
I WANT TO THANK MADAM CLERK ANGELA CALVILLO FOR YOUR
GUIDANCE AND SUPPORT THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS.
I WANT TO THANK OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS FOR GOING ABOVE
AND BEYOND TO HELP OUR CONSTITUENTS IN DISTRICT NINE.
I WANT TO THANK MAYOR LARY AND HIS STAFF FOR THEIR
COMPASSION AND ASSISTANCE TO MY OFFICE ESPECIALLY AROUND SMALL
BUSINESS AND PUBLIC SAFETY CONCERNS.
AND I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK MY CONSTITUENTS THE COMMUNITY
LEADERS, COMMUNITY GROUPS FROM BERNAL, THE MISSION AND PORTOLA
WHO I HAVE THE HONOR OF SERVING IN THIS CHAIR.
I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE OUTPOURING OF SUPPORT.
WHEN I WAS IN MY HOSPITAL AND DURING MY LEAVE.
SO THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH FOR YOUR GRACE AND I'M SO PROUD
AND HONORED TO BE BACK. >> THANK YOU, GENTLEMEN.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER, IT'S GOOD
TO HAVE YOU BACK AND IT'S CREDIT TO YOU THAT YOUR OFFICE
HAS PERFORMED SO WELL IN YOUR TIME OUT.
SO THANKS TO THEM FROM US AS WELL.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
>> YES, THANK YOU. THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES ALL OF YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE IN PERSON IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER ROOM TWO 52ND FLOOR OF CITY HALL.
AND WHEN YOU ARE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE, THE PROCEEDINGS ARE
AIRING LIVE ON AS OF G OF TV'S CABLE CHANNEL DEPENDING ON YOUR
PROVIDER OR YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVESTREAM AT S.F. GOV TV BORG.
YOU MAY ALSO SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING BY SENDING
AN EMAIL TO BOX AT S.F. GOV DAWG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE
JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS IS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY
HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94194102 IF YOU NEED
TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE
MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY ACT OR TO
REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE TWO
BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA, PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH
FOUR. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE.
IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED
SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
THESE ITEMS ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR.
>> SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I'M
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE SUPPORT ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CHANGE THE NAME OF THE STATUS OF WOMEN
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE PROGRAM FUND TO THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
SHELTER BASE PROGRAM FUND TO REVISE THE PURPOSE OF THE FUND
ESTABLISHED THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT OR ANOTHER AGENCY DESIGNATED BY THE MAYOR AS
ADMINISTRATOR OF THE FUND WITH DELEGATED DUTIES AND TO UPDATE
PROVISIONS REGARDING THE FUND TO REFLECT STATE LAW CHANGES
RELATING TO FISCAL ACTED BY THE COUNTY CLERK FOR THE FUND.
LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE ENVIRONMENT, HEALTH, LABOR
AND EMPLOYMENT PART PLANNING POLICE PUBLIC WORKS SUBDIVISION
TRANSPORTATION AND BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION CODES TO
MODIFY NUMEROUS REPORTING REQUIREMENTS ADDITIONALLY TO
REMOVE VARIOUS OBSOLETE REPORTING REQUIREMENTS
ELIMINATE DEFUNCT FUNDS AGENCIES PLANS, STAFFING
REQUIREMENTS AND PROGRAMS TO MAKE OTHER UPDATES AND OTHER
CONFORMING AMENDMENTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THIS ORDINANCE HAS BEEN AROUND
FOR A WHILE. I WANT TO THANK THE MEMBERS OF
GAO FOR HEARING IT AND PASSING IT TO THE FULL BOARD SINCE THE
GAO HAD ITS HEARING YESTERDAY WE ACTUALLY GOT SOME
CORRESPONDENCE EXPRESSING CONCERNS FROM FOLKS IN THE
LOCAL SMALL BUSINESS COMMUNITY THAT I THINK WE WANT TO SPEND A
LITTLE TIME LOOKING AT. I THINK THERE MAY BE SOME OTHER
QUESTIONS AND CONCERNS THAT MAY HAVE WE'RE HEARING ABOUT FROM
COLLEAGUES. SO I THINK IT WOULD MAKE SENSE
TO GIVE THIS GIVE US A LITTLE BIT OF TIME TO THINK THROUGH
THESE ISSUES AND FIGURE OUT IF WE NEED TO MAKE AMENDMENTS OR
WHAT WE NEED TO DO WITH US. SO I WOULD LIKE TO I WILL MOVE
THAT WE CONTINUE THIS ITEM FOR TWO WEEKS.
MADAM CLERK SECTION NINE THAT'S BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR
WALTON AND THAT IS UNTIL JULY 14TH.
>> JULY 14TH. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN JUST KIND
OF WANT TO UNDERSTAND WHAT EVEN BROUGHT THIS ABOUT.
WHAT WAS THE PURPOSE OF THIS LEGISLATION, THIS ORDINANCE
EVEN BROUGHT IT ABOUT WELL OH GOSH.
>> WHERE WHERE WHERE YOU GOT NO WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A
CONVERSATION ABOUT SO THIS THERE ARE A TON OF REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS BUILT INTO OUR CODES OFTEN WHEN WE PASS
LEGISLATION AND SUPERVISORS FOR DECADES NOW HAVE PASSED
LEGISLATION ON VARIOUS TOPICS OF CONCERN TO THE PUBLIC.
OFTEN THEY WILL ADD A REPORTING REQUIREMENT ABOUT SOMETHING
THAT SEEMS VERY IMPORTANT IN THAT MOMENT AND THAT MEANS
THAT EITHER ON AN ANNUAL BASIS OR LONGER THAN ANNUALLY THERE
ARE CITY STAFF WHO SPEND TIME PREPARING REPORTS.
MANY OF THOSE REPORTS END UP BEING READ BY NO ONE.
SOME OF THOSE REPORTS MADE SENSE 20 YEARS AGO BUT DO NOT
MAKE SENSE NOW. SO OUR CITY ATTORNEY AND HIS
TEAM TOOK IT UPON THEMSELVES MORE THAN A YEAR AGO THAT A
CITY ATTORNEY BROUGHT THIS TO US.
THE CITY ATTORNEY BROUGHT IT TO US.
SO NO, NOBODY FROM COMMUNITY CAME IN AND SAID THIS IS NOT A
THERE'S NOT A HUE AND CALL FROM THE BROADER COMMUNITY TO CLEAN
UP OUR CODES. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU
SO MUCH. I'M NOT GOING TO BELABOR THE
POINT. >> I AM GRATEFUL THAT YOU ARE
CONTINUING THIS. I'M NOT SURE TWO WEEKS IS
ENOUGH BUT I'LL GO WITH IT. I THINK THAT IT IS A 308 PAGE
PIECE OF LEGISLATION. IT'S A LOT AND I'M NOT ON GAO.
I DID WATCH SOME OF THE CONVERSATION AND I'M
APPRECIATIVE OF MY COLLEAGUES WEIGHING IN ON IT.
I WENT HOME AND I RAN IT THROUGH CLYDE AND I DO THINK
MOST OF IT IS CLEANUP. IT IS STUFF THAT IS
INCONSISTENCIES IN THE CODE. OUR CODE IS A FRANKENSTEIN.
THERE ARE CONTRADICTING STATEMENTS THERE ARE
CONTRADICTING CODES. THEY'RE OBSOLETE.
THINGS ARE THINGS THAT DON'T EXIST ANYMORE AND THERE IS A
PORTION OF THIS LEGISLATION THAT I ACTUALLY THINK IT'S A
POLICY DECISION THAT WE SHOULD THINK ABOUT DO WE STILL NEED TO
KEEP TRACK OF HOW MANY WOMEN ARE DEPICTED IN OUR PUBLIC ART?
DO WE STILL NEED TO KEEP TRACK WHETHER WOMEN ARE BEING PAID
THE SAME AS MEN DO? WE STILL NEED TO UNDERSTAND HOW
MANY RENTAL APARTMENTS ARE BEING CONVERTED TO
CONDOMINIUMS? HOW OFTEN?
>> SO I THINK THAT THERE'S A BUNCH OF STUFF THAT IS IN HERE
AND I WILL ACKNOWLEDGE IT IS THE MINORITY OF THINGS THAT WE
NEED TO ACTUALLY HAVE A POLICY CONVERSATION.
IS THIS STILL APPROPRIATE? IS IT NO LONGER NECESSARY?
CAN WE ABSORB IT INTO THE LARGE REPORT?
>> PERHAPS. BUT I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, NOW
THAT WE ARE ABLE THROUGH AI TO LOOK AT DATA SETS AND LOTS OF
INFORMATION AND BE MORE EFFICIENT IN HOW WE LOOK AT IT,
OUR PROCESSES YOU KNOW LIKE WE STILL HAVE A HUMAN PROCESS
AND MOST IMPORTANTLY I THINK AS A LEGISLATIVE BRANCH WE HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY TO THE PUBLIC TO MAKE SURE THAT THEY UNDERSTAND
WHAT WE'RE DOING AND I'M NOT SURE THAT'S THE CASE YET.
SO I AM APPRECIATIVE OF A LITTLE BIT OF TIME SO THAT I
CAN CALL MY WOMEN AND THE LBB FOLKS AND EVERYONE AND SAY IS
THIS OKAY WITH YOU? BECAUSE I DO THINK THAT IT IS A
LITTLE BIT APPROPRIATE NOT YOU KNOW, SAYING THAT THIS IS NOT
WORTH THE WORK OR THAT SOMEBODY HASN'T DONE THEIR JOB.
I AM VERY, VERY APPRECIATIVE OF THE CITY ATTORNEY TAKING THIS
ON. I HAVE BEEN THROUGH LOTS OF
CODE CLEANUP OF THE PLANNING CODE WHICH IS IN ITSELF A
FRANKENSTEIN. SO I APPRECIATE HOW MUCH IT IS
. I JUST THINK IT TAKES HUMAN
BEINGS A LITTLE BIT OF TIME AND FEELS TO LIKE WRAP THEIR
HEADS AROUND WHAT'S GOING ON. THANK YOU.
THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT I MEAN I THINK THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT THE
PROBLEM IS AT THE MOMENT IS THAT I DO NOT UNDERSTAND WHY IS
IN THE LEGISLATION 300 SOMETHING PAGES OF IT BUT WHAT
ACTUALLY MULTIPLE SUBJECT COULDN'T BE BROKEN INTO
DIFFERENT PIECES OF LEGISLATION TO ALLOW A FIRST OF ALL FIRST
AND FOREMOST A SUMMARY OF THE LEGISLATION THAT IS MORE
DIGESTIBLE FOR THE PUBLIC AND MYSELF INCLUDED.
AND I WOULD SAY YOU KNOW, AS BEING A NAY FOR MORE THAN 20
YEARS LIKE I WILL I WILL CONCEDE TO THE FACT TOO THAT
TODAY I WAS WALKING IN TO TO THIS CHAMBER IF IT WASN'T FOR
THE CONTINUANCE PROBABLY BE VOTING AGAINST THIS VERY
LEGISLATION FOR A COUPLE OF REASONS AND ONE IS WE LITERALLY
JUST FINISHING OFF THE BUDGET. >> I WISH I HAD MORE TIME TO
TRULY GO THROUGH THE LEGISLATION AND GREATER
DETAILS. BUT AGAIN OF COURSE IN LIGHT OF
THE LETTER COMING FROM YOU KNOW THAT I'LL BE COMMUNITY BUT NOT
JUST THAT BUT JUST ALONG THE WAY I THINK EVEN AT ITS
INTRODUCTION WHEN CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU HAD INDICATED THIS
WAS REALLY WRITTEN BY I. I MEAN I THINK SINCE THEN
THERE'S THERE'S DIFFERENT INTERPRETATION HOW IT CAME
ABOUT. BUT I DO KNOW THAT THERE ARE
ACTUALLY MODIBO CITY DEPARTMENTS WERE HAVING A
DIFFICULT TIME WITH THIS LEGISLATION AND TOOK THEM A
LONG TIME TO TRY TO TWEAK IT WHICH IS THE REASON WHY IT TOOK
QUITE SOME TIME TO GO THROUGH TO TO ACTUALLY BE HEARD AT
RULES AT ALL WHICH IS TO SAY I AM NOT READY TO VOTE ON IT
SHOULD I BE ASKED TO VOTE FOR IT TODAY AND EVEN IN TWO WEEKS
IT WILL BE A NO VOTE. >> I JUST WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR
ABOUT THAT BUT I WOULD ABSOLUTELY OPEN TO IN THE TWO
WEEKS TIME SHOULD PRESENT AMENDMENT AND THE MAYOR AND YOU
KNOW OR NOT MAYOR SORRY CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU HAS DECIDED
TO SAY YOU KNOW WHAT, THERE'S ENOUGH CONCERN AND THAT PEOPLE
ACTUALLY ARE OPEN MINDED TO HEAR THESE CONCERNS AND BE MORE
THAN WILLING TO UNDERSTAND TO BREAK THIS WITH THIS BIG PIECE
OF LEGISLATION AND TO ACTUALLY SUBJECT SINGLE SUBJECT
LEGISLATION TO ALLOW THE PUBLIC AND THE VERY LEGISLATURE LIKE
THE POLICYMAKER NOT HAVE TO VOTE ON IT TO GIVEN THAT
OPPORTUNITY TO REALLY TO UNDERSTAND AND BE ABLE TO GIVE
MEANINGFUL AMENDMENTS, THEN I, I, I WOULD LOVE TO SEE THAT.
>> LET ME ALSO JUST SAY OVERALL WHAT THIS LEGISLATION AND OTHER
LEGISLATION INCLUDING THOSE THAT'S CURRENTLY ON THE BALLOT
THAT WILL BE ON THE BALLOT THIS FALL AND WHAT WE ALREADY HAVE
DONE WITH STREAMLINE TASK FORCE WHICH I DON'T THINK I'M
ACTUALLY IN THE OPINION OF THE MAJORITY OF THIS BOARD HERE AT
THE MOMENT. >> I THINK THAT THERE ARE MANY
LEGISLATION IN THIS YEAR INTRODUCE OR LIKE THE PROCESS
FROM LAST YEAR THAT P. S MEALING THROUGH PIECE BY
PIECE TAKING AWAY AND CHIPPING AWAY TRANSPARENCY C OF CITY
GOVERNMENT AND THE INTEGRITY OF CITY GOVERNMENT TO MAKE SURE
THAT IT IS TRANSPARENT TO EVERY DE SAN FRANCISCAN.
SO THAT'S JUST MY OVERALL IMPRESSION BUT ALSO JUST
IN DISAGREEMENTS OF HOW WE APPROACH ALL THESE POLICIES.
I DO BELIEVE THAT I KNOW THAT THERE'S A SENTIMENT OUT THERE
THAT WE JUST NEED TO THROW EVERYTHING AWAY SO THAT WE IT'S
MAKE IT EASIER AND BETTER. I THINK THAT'S NOT THE RIGHT
APPROACH. I THINK THE APPROACH IS TO HOW
DO WE BE MORE SURGICAL IN TWEAKING CITY GOVERNMENTS
AND REGULATIONS AND POLICIES TO MAKE IT MORE WORK MORE
EFFICIENT. >> BUT IT'S NOT TO JUST REMOVE
EVERYTHING TOGETHER. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH
PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN SURPRISE, SURPRISE.
CHERYL IN THE CONVERSATIONS ABOUT TAKING TIME TO GO THROUGH
SPECIFIC AMENDMENTS AND LOOKING THROUGH THIS, I JUST WANT TO
MAKE SURE THAT CERTAIN PEOPLE DO GET CREDIT FOR THE LARGE
AMOUNT OF TIME THAT THEY SPENT ON THIS LEGISLATION.
SPECIFICALLY I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN AND HER STAFF
WHO DID SPEND AN INORDINATE AMOUNT OF TIME ON ASPECTS OF
THIS MAKING IT BETTER. I THINK YOU AND YOUR TEAM
DESERVE A LOT OF CREDIT ESPECIALLY CHARLIE.
HOPEFULLY YOU'RE WATCHING AND ALSO LORENZO ROSAS AND MY
TEAM WORK WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
A LOT OF WORK HAS GONE INTO THIS AND I THINK SOMETIMES WHEN
WE TALK ABOUT TRANSPARENCY I THINK TRANSPARENCY IS WILDLY
IMPORTANT BUT SOMETIMES WE DECIDE TO BE TRANSPARENT WHILE
IN A IN ACTUALITY DROWNING PEOPLE IN INFORMATION AND THAT
BECOMES THE COMPLETE OPPOSITE OF TRANSPARENCY.
AND THIS LEGISLATION IS SO LARGE BECAUSE WE AS A CITY HAVE
DONE SUCH A BAD JOB HOLDING OURSELVES ACCOUNTABLE FOR WHAT
TRANSPARENCY ACTUALLY MEANS. AND SO I DON'T LIKE THAT THIS
LEGISLATION IS ENORMOUS BECAUSE IT'S A REFLECTION OF HOW WE AS
A CITY AND A BODY HAVE BEEN HONEST WITH THIS WITH THE
RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND WE HAVEN'T BEEN.
SO I THINK WE DO NEED TO TAKE A MASSIVE WHACK AT IT.
I DON'T LOVE THE IDEA THAT WE'RE CONTINUING THIS BUT I GET
IT. I THINK THAT'S OKAY.
WE CAN ALWAYS WORK THINGS TO MAKE THEM BETTER BUT I DO WANT
TO MAKE SURE THAT THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN WORKING ON THIS
GET THE CREDIT AND AGAIN THAT'S SUPERVISOR CHEN IN HER OFFICE.
LORENZO ROSE IS IN MY OFFICE AS WELL AS PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT
AND HIS TEAM AND DEFINITELY THE CITY ATTORNEY WHO WORKED THEIR
BUTTS OFF ON THIS. SO THEY DESERVE A LOT OF CREDIT
FOR DIGGING IN VERY, VERY DEEPLY.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL I WILL ECHO
THE THANKS TO SUPERVISOR CHEN AND HER STAFF FOR ENGAGING
SERIOUSLY WITH THIS LEGISLATION AND TO YOU AND YOUR STAFF WHO
WORKED THROUGH WITH HER OFFICE SOME OF THE CONCERNS THAT THEY
HAD RAISED. I ALSO HAD REQUESTED AMENDMENTS
TO THE ORIGINAL LEGISLATION WHICH I WOULD NOTE WAS
INTRODUCED ONE YEAR AGO. >> SO IT THE LEGISLATION HAS
BEEN AROUND FOR A VERY LONG TIME.
THE CITY ATTORNEY HAS PREPARED A VERY HELPFUL DOCUMENT WHICH
IS PART OF THE RECORD WHICH GOES THROUGH EVERY SINGLE
CHANGE DESCRIBES WHAT IT IS FOR THOSE WHO HAVE NOT HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY TO LOOK AT THAT AND FIGURE OUT WHAT MIGHT BE OF
CONCERN TO YOU, I WOULD ENCOURAGE YOU TO DO THAT SOONER
RATHER THAN LATER. IDEALLY THIS WORK HAPPENS PRIOR
TO COMMITTEE AND AGAIN THIS LEGISLATION HAS BEEN AROUND FOR
A WHILE BUT I ALSO UNDERSTAND THAT HAVING SOMETHING GET TO
THE FULL BOARD TENDS TO FOCUS PEOPLE'S ATTENTIONS AND SO I AM
FINE WITH CONTINUING THE CONVERSATION LIKE SUPERVISOR
CHERYL I DON'T WANT TO TALK ABOUT THIS FOREVER AND I DO
WANT TO GET SOMETHING DONE BECAUSE THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE AND THE DEPARTMENTS THEMSELVES ACTUALLY DID REAL
WORK TO IDENTIFY WHAT THEY PERCEIVED AS PAIN POINTS
AND THINGS THAT THEY BELIEVED WERE KEEPING THEM FROM TURNING
TO MORE IMPORTANT ITEMS OF BUSINESS.
SUPERVISOR CHAN MY APOLOGIES PRESIDENT VANDEMAN BUT I THINK
THAT I JUST WANT TO ADD A NOTE THIS TO THIS THOUGH I DO KNOW
IT'S BEEN INTRODUCED FOR A WHILE AND YOU KNOW EVERYONE
SHOULD HAVE THE CHANCE TO LIKE I SHOULD HAVE ALREADY TAKEN THE
OPPORTUNITY TO LOOK AT IT. I, I THINK WHAT I'M ALSO TRYING
TO SAY IS THAT ISN'T JUST FOR US BUT I THINK THAT MY QUESTION
AND I AND I AND I THINK THAT CITY ATTORNEY CHIU KNOWS IS
BEST BECAUSE HE BOTH BEEN A YOU KNOW ON THE BOARD SUPERVISORS
AS YOU KNOW AND NOW AS OUR CITY ATTORNEY BUT I I KIND OF
QUESTION THE SORT OF WHILE IT'S BEING INTRODUCED AND WE ALL
KNOW THAT WE CAN INTRODUCE LEGISLATION BUT NEVER PAY
ATTENTION TO STAKEHOLDERS AND HOW IT ACTUALLY IN IT'S
KIND OF PIGGYBACK ON WHAT SUPERVISOR WALTON KIND OF SAID
IT'S LIKE IT'S NOT BEING BOUGHT ON BY THE COMMUNITY BUT IT'S
BEING BROUGHT ON BY CITY ATTORNEY CHIU THAT'S FINE
AND CITY DEPARTMENTS THEN HAD A CHANCE TO SORT OF LOOK AT IT
BECAUSE THEN THEY ARE DIRECTLY IMPACT HOW HOW THEY REPORT BACK
TO THIS BODY AND CREATING REPORTING BUT AGAIN THE
STAKEHOLDERS WHICH IS REALLY THE GENERAL PUBLIC I AM JUST
QUESTIONING THE OUTREACH AND CONVERSATION AND WHAT HAS
IT BEEN LIKE FOR FOR THE PEOPLE THAT MAYBE COUNTING ON SOME OF
THESE RECORDS AND THAT WE DON'T KNOW IF THEY ARE READING THESE
RECORDS BUT THEN PERHAPS THEY ARE I KNOW THAT CIVIL GRAND
JURIES SOMETIMES DEPEND ARE DEPENDENT ON THESE RECORDS.
SO I AM I AGAIN I I'M I JUST HAVE A LOT OF QUESTIONS ABOUT
THIS SO I'M NOT SAYING THAT IT WASN'T INTRODUCED IN A TIMELY
FASHION THAT PEOPLE WILL HAVE ENOUGH TIME.
BUT I, I THINK IT'S ALSO JUST THE APPROACH OF HOW WE APPROACH
TO THIS LEGISLATIVE PROCESS IN TERMS OF OUTREACH TO
STAKEHOLDERS. >> THANK YOU.
>> MELGAR OKAY, I'M GOING TO BE SHORT AND THEN I'LL LEAVE IT
ALONE. I WANTED TO ACKNOWLEDGE WHAT
SUPERVISOR CHERYL BROUGHT UP. I DO THINK THAT OUR CODE IS
CUMBERSOME AND COMPLICATED AND NOT ACCESSIBLE AND THAT AS
YOU KNOW OUR CITY HAS GROWN AND GOTTEN MORE COMPLICATED.
IT HAS BECOME MORE SO. SO I ACTUALLY SUPPORT THE GOAL
OF THIS LEGISLATION. I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT I PUT
ON THE RECORD THAT I'M NOT ASCRIBING ANY MOTIVATION.
YOU KNOW, IT'S NOT THAT I'M SAYING THAT THERE IS A DESIRE
FOR LACK OF TRANSPARENCY OR ANYTHING BUT I DO WANT TO
UNDERSCORE THAT I THINK IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE UPHOLD
THE INTEGRITY OF OUR LEGISLATIVE PROCESS
IN NOTWITHSTANDING IT HAVING GONE TO JAIL AND FOLKS PUTTING
IN A LOT OF WORK. I ACKNOWLEDGE THE AIDES DO
GOD'S WORK AND YOUR AIDES IN PARTICULAR THERE ARE OTHER
CONSTITUENTS THAT PERHAPS WERE NOT IN JUST, YOU KNOW, YOUR
AREA OF INTEREST THAT ARE OUT THERE THAT HAVE CONCERNS.
AND SO I DO THINK OUR PROCESS IS THERE FOR A REASON THAT WE
ARE THE PEOPLE'S HOUSE, THAT WE ARE CHARGED WITH MAKING SURE
THAT WE GET THE FEEDBACK FROM ALL THESE DIFFERENT
CONSTITUENCIES AND THE DIVERSITY OF THIS BOARD IS ITS
BEAUTY BECAUSE WE ARE ALL IN TOUCH WITH DIFFERENT
CONSTITUENCIES, DIFFERENT COMMUNITIES WE HEAR FROM
DIFFERENT PEOPLE. SO SOMETHING THAT IS 308 PAGES
LONG THAT RUNS ACROSS MULTIPLE CODES AND MULTIPLE REPORTS OVER
TIME DESERVES TO HAVE THAT SORT OF YOU KNOW, RESPECT OF THE
INTEGRITY OF OUR PROCESS SO THAT WE CAN HEAR FROM FOLKS
AND IT MAY BE THAT WE PARSE IT EXACTLY WITH EVERY WORD THAT IT
IS. I JUST THINK THAT OUR PROCESS
IS IMPORTANT AND THAT IT NEEDS TO BE DIGESTIBLE NOT JUST US
BUT TO THE PUBLIC AND THAT WE YOU KNOW, HAVE THAT
RESPONSIBILITY. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU. >> PRESIDENT BENJAMIN I AM NOT
GOING TO BELABOR THE POINT. I DO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHEN'S OFFICE AND SUPERVISOR SHERYL'S OFFICE FOR THE WORK
YOU HAD TO DO THIS WORK BECAUSE IT WAS BROUGHT TO US THIS
ENORMOUS DOCUMENT. BUT I WILL JUST SAY THIS THAT
WE HAVE LARGER ISSUES TO WORRY ABOUT IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND THAT'S WHY ONE OF THE REASONS WHY THIS IS
PROBLEMATIC FOR ME AS WELL WE'VE GOT REAL THINGS TO WORRY
ABOUT AND WE SHOULD WE SHOULDN'T BE SPENDING THIS MUCH
TIME ON SOMETHING THAT WAS BROUGHT BY IT WAS NOT BROUGHT
BY THE PEOPLE. IT WAS NOT BROUGHT BY ONE OF US
AND QUITE FRANKLY THE WAY IT WAS BROUGHT THE CONVERSATIONS
WE'VE HAD HAVE BEEN PROBLEM AT IT.
AND SO I WOULD JUST SAY THAT AND I'LL SAVE WHAT I REALLY
WANT TO SAY FOR WHEN IT COMES BACK TO THIS BODY BUT WE'VE GOT
BIGGER THINGS TO ADDRESS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> OKAY. >> WITH THAT, A MOTION IS MADE
TO CONTINUE THIS UNTIL WHAT DATE?
JULY 14TH. JULY 14TH.
IT HAS BEEN SECONDED. COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION. WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> THE MOTION PASSES. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
SEVEN. >> ITEM SEVEN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE POLICE CODE TO MODIFY PROVISIONS OF THE FAIR CHANCE
ORDINANCE THAT REGULATE THE USE OF CRIMINAL HISTORY IN CERTAIN
EMPLOYMENT AND HOUSING DECISIONS SPECIFICALLY BY
PROVIDING THAT EMPLOYERS AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROVIDERS MAY NOT USE OUT-OF-STATE CRIMINAL
CONVICTIONS OR ARRESTS FOR CONDUCT THAT IS LAWFUL
IN CALIFORNIA RELATED TO ABORTION RELATED HEALTH CARE,
DRUG PERFORMANCES, GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AND SPONTANEOUS
ABORTION AS DEFINED IN MAKING CERTAIN EMPLOYMENT OR HOUSING
RELATED DECISIONS OR INCREASING ADMINISTRATIVE PENALTIES FOR
VIOLATIONS AND INCREASING LIQUIDATED DAMAGES AVAILABLE
IN A LAWSUIT. >> COLLEAGUES, LET'S TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING ITEM.
>> YEAH. >> APOLOGIES, MR. PRESIDENT.
I JUMPED THE GUN. ITEM EIGHT RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR OR HIS DESIGNEE TO CAST AN ASSESSMENT
BALLOT IN THE AFFIRMATIVE FOR THE PROPOSED RENEWAL
AND EXPANSION OF A PROPERTY AND BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT
DISTRICT KNOWN AS THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT WITH
RESPECT TO CERTAIN PARCELS OF REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY
THAT WOULD BE SUBJECT TO ASSESSMENT IN SAID DISTRICT.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE ITEM NINE
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT'S
USE OF EQUIPMENT POLICY 2025 ANNUAL REPORT CONSISTENT WITH
THE CRITERIA SET FORTH IN STATE LAW.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER TEN. >> ITEM TEN.
THIS IS A CHARTER AMENDMENT FIRST DRAFT TO AMEND THE
CHARTER OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO AUTHORIZE
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A MUNICIPAL FINANCE CORPORATION
AND PUBLIC BANK AS NONPROFIT CORPORATIONS AND TO SET FORTH
THE MISSION PRINCIPLES AND GOVERNANCE STRUCTURE OF
THOSE CORPORATIONS AS AT AN ELECTION TO BE HELD ON NOVEMBER
3RD, 2026 AND PURSUANT TO PROVISIONS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS RULES OF ORDER 2.22.7.
AT LEAST SIX DAYS MUST INTERVENE BETWEEN THE FIRST
APPEARANCE OF A CHARTER AMENDMENT BEFORE THE BOARD AS A
REFERRAL FROM COMMITTEE AND ANY BOARD ORDER OF SUBMISSION TO
THE ELECTORATE. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
BOARD PRESIDENT. >> COLLEAGUE I ASKED FOR YOUR
SUPPORT TODAY FOR THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT TO ESTABLISH TO
ESTABLISH THE FRAMEWORK AND GOVERNANCE FOR OUR
MUNICIPAL FINANCE CORPORATION AND PUBLIC BANK.
>> WHEN WE LOOK AROUND OUR CITY WE SEE CLAIRE MIGHT GET GIFTS
FOR SOME OF THE CITY'S MOST URGENT PRIORITIES.
THESE ARE GAPS WHERE SMALL BUSINESS BREACHED WHERE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING STARTS AND WHERE CLIMATE PROJECTS GO
UNFUNDED. WE KNOW THAT SOME THINGS ARE
TOO IMPORTANT TO FALL THROUGH THE CRACKS RIGOROUS DUE DUE TO
DILIGENCE FROM FINANCIAL EXPERTS, POLICY MAKERS
AND COMMUNITY STAKEHOLDERS HAS CONFIRMED WHAT THE DATA TELLS
US. >> WE CAN FEEL THOSE MARKET
GAPS. WE CAN BE A PUBLIC BANK THAT
IT'S BOTH FINANCIALLY PROFITABLE AND SOCIALLY
TRANSFORMATIVE. THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT
ESTABLISHED STRONG GOOD GOVERNANCE STRUCTURES WHEN AN
OVERSIGHT BODY SELECTED BY THE TREASURER COMPTROLLER, CITY
ATTORNEY, MAYOR AND BOTH SUPERVISORS AND A BOARD OF
DIRECTORS COMPOSED OF SKEW BANKING PROFESSIONALS, BANKERS
AND WHO UPHOLD FINANCIAL INDUSTRY BEST PRACTICES
AND RIGOROUS FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT.
>> A PUBLIC BANK WOULD OPEN THE DOORS TO BUILD AN ENGINE FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING A LIFELINE FOR STRUGGLING SMALL BUSINESS
AND THE FINANCIAL BACKBONE FOR OUR CLIMATE GOALS.
LET US USE EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL TO KEEP THIS CITY
AFFORDABLE AND TO DRIVE AN ECONOMIC RECOVERY THAT LEAVES
NO ONE BEHIND. >> LET US TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE
PATHWAY THAT HAS BEEN CREATED FOR US BY OUR STATE LAWMAKERS.
>> I WANT TO THANK OUR TREASURER, THE COMPTROLLER,
CITY ATTORNEY, LOCAL AND ALL THE ESTEEMED MEMBERS OF THE
REINVESTMENT WORKING GROUP AND THE TIRELESS ADVOCACY OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO POP-UP BANK COALITION.
>> THEY HAVE ALL LAID THE FOUNDATION FOR THIS CHARTER
AMENDMENTS. I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY EARLY
CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR FIELDER WALTON SUPERVISOR MELGAR
AND SUPERVISOR MATT MOORE. >> AND I LOOK FORWARD TO YOUR
SUPPORT TO BRING THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT TO THE VOTERS OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANKS, PRESIDENT GILMAN.
>> I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR TAKING THIS
UP. I WANT TO THANK CHARLIE AND HER
OFFICE FOR WORKING TIRELESSLY ON THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT AS
HAS BEEN MANY YEARS COMING. GOING BACK TO SUPERVISOR JOHN
BELLOWS IN 2008 DOING SOME WORK ON A PUBLIC BANK
AND SUPERVISORS SANDY FEUER AS WELL AS PRESIDENT PRESTON WHO
ESTABLISHED THE REINVESTMENT WORKING GROUP AND ON THAT
WORKING GROUP WERE REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE
BANKING WORLD, FROM THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE, FROM THE
TREASURER AND TAX COLLECTOR. AND I ALSO WANT TO WANT TO
THANK THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANK COALITION SPECIFICALLY
MEASURE STIER AS WELL AS KRISTEN EVANS AND SYLVIA CHEA
BOTH AT A SAFE AND READY TO GO AS AND FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK
IN GETTING THIS STATE LAW TO WHERE IT IS.
ESTABLISHED IN 2019 THAT ACTUALLY LEGALIZED PUBLIC
BANKING AND THEN GETTING IT TO WHERE IT IS NOW BEFORE US TODAY
. SO THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK LAF CO-EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR COLIN
SAMURAI AND CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE SUPERVISOR WANG
PRESIDENT MADELINE COLLEAGUES. THANK YOU.
I DO NOT BELIEVE CREATING A FRAMEWORK FOR A PUBLIC BANK IS
THE RIGHT PATH FOR THE CITY AT THIS TIME.
RIGHT NOW SAN FRANCISCANS WANT US TO TAKE CARE OF THE BASICS.
THEY ARE ASKING US TO MAKE GOVERNMENT WORK BETTER TO SPEND
CAREFULLY AND TO DELIVER RESULTS IN THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THEY'RE ASKING ME ABOUT MUNI RELIABILITY.
THEY'RE ASKING HOW LONG IT TAKES TO GET A PERMIT.
THEY'RE ASKING ABOUT THE SAFETY AND CLEANLINESS OF OUR STREETS
AND THE QUALITY OF OUR SCHOOLS AND WHETHER OUR GOVERNMENT'S
LAWS AND POLICIES ARE RESPONSIVE TO THEIR ACTUAL
NEEDS. THEY'RE FRUSTRATED WITH CITY
HALL PROMISING BIG THINGS AND DELIVERING GESTURES.
THEY'RE WATCHING A STRUGGLE FOR RESPONSIBILITIES WE ALREADY
HAVE. WE'RE MANAGING A SIGNIFICANT
BUDGET DEFICIT. WE'RE MAKING HARD CHOICES ABOUT
WHICH SERVICES TO FUND AND WHICH PROGRAMS TO SCALE
BACK. WE'RE ASKING OUR CITY
DEPARTMENTS AND PARTNERS TO ABSORB CUTS.
IN A MOMENT LIKE THIS ASKING VOTERS TO COMMIT SAN FRANCISCO
TO POTENTIALLY RUNNING A FINANCIAL INSTITUTION IS ASKING
FOR TRUST THE CITY HAS NOT YET EARNED A PUBLIC BANK INVOLVES
DECISIONS ABOUT DEPOSITS, LENDING, CREDIT REGULATION
AND RISK MANAGEMENT. THOSE DECISIONS CARRY REAL
FINANCIAL CONSEQUENCES. THEY DEMAND INSTITUTIONAL
DISCIPLINE INSULATION FROM POLITICAL PRESSURE,
TRANSPARENCY AND DEEP BANKING EXPERTISE.
>> OUR CITY TRACKS OUR CITY'S TRACK RECORD SHOWS THAT MEETING
THOSE DEMANDS IS HARDER THAN IT SOUNDS EVEN FOR INSTITUTIONS
DESIGNED WITH THE RIGHT INTENTIONS.
PUBLIC BANKS HAVE A LONG HISTORY IN THIS COUNTRY.
THEY HAVE BEEN TRIED FOR TWO CENTURIES AND MOST DID NOT
LAST. THE ONE THAT SURVIVES IN NORTH
DAKOTA DEPENDS ON STATE FUNDED DEPOSITS FED BY OIL REVENUE
AND AN ENTIRE STATE ECONOMY TO LEND ACROSS CONDITIONS.
>> SAN FRANCISCO COULD NOT REPLICATE THE BANKS THAT FAILED
TENDED TO FAIL THE SAME WAY THEY LEANT ON POLITICAL
DIRECTION RATHER THAN ON REPAYMENT.
AND WHEN THOSE LOANS WENT BAD IT WAS THE PUBLIC THAT ENDED UP
BEARING THE LOSS. WE ALSO SHOULD ASK WHETHER
THERE ARE LOWER RISK WAYS TO ACHIEVE THE SAME GOALS.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS COMMUNITY LENDERS, CREDIT UNIONS,
NONPROFIT LOAN FUNDS AND OTHER FINANCIAL PARTNERS DOING WORK
IN THIS SPACE. THEIR LENDING RIGHT NOW TO THE
SMALL BUSINESSES, IMMIGRANT ENTREPRENEURS AND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING DEVELOPERS WE WANT TO SUPPORT BEFORE CREATING A NEW
FINANCIAL PUBLIC FINANCIAL INSTITUTION.
WE SHOULD LOOK AT WHETHER WE CAN BETTER STRENGTHEN THE
INSTITUTIONS ALREADY DOING THIS WORK.
A COMMITMENT OF THE SCALE CALLS FOR A CLEAR PICTURE OF HOW IT
WOULD BE FUNDED, HOW IT WOULD OPERATE AND HOW IT WOULD BE
HELD ACCOUNTABLE. THAT PICTURE IS NOT THERE YET.
I DO NOT SUPPORT GOING IN THIS DIRECTION.
I WANT US TO FOCUS ON THE BASICS OF GOOD GOVERNMENT
AND ON EARNING THE TRUST. A COMMITMENT LIKE THIS WOULD
ASK OF US. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU, COLLEAGUES.
>> I JUST WANT TO SPEAK AND A VERY AFFIRMATIVE SUPPORT OF
THIS LEGISLATION AND THIS BALLOT MEASURE FOR A COUPLE OF
REASONS. ONE, THERE'S A SHOT CLOCK ON
BEING ABLE TO INSTITUTE THIS THIS IS ABOUT MAINTAINING THE
OPTION FOR SAN FRANCISCO TO CREATE A PUBLIC BANK IN THE
FUTURE. THERE IS A STATE DEADLINE THAT
IS COMING UP AND THIS IS NOT ABOUT FUNDING THAT
INFRASTRUCTURE TODAY. IT'S ABOUT ALLOWING FOR THE
OPTIONALITY FOR US TO FUND IT IN THE FUTURE.
SO I DON'T VIEW THIS AS A TRADEOFF BETWEEN OUR CURRENT
BUDGET AND OUR CURRENT PRIORITIES.
IT'S ABOUT INVESTING FOR THE FUTURE FOR WHEN WE ARE
IN BETTER CIRCUMSTANCES THAT WE CAN INVEST IN THAT AND IF WE
DON'T PASS THIS WE LOSE OUT ON THAT OPPORTUNITY THAT HAS BEEN
AFFORDED TO US BY THE STATE. >> SECOND IS THE BENEFIT OF
THIS IS ACTUALLY THAT THIS IS GOING TO SUPPORT OUR EXISTING
INSTITUTIONS. THE WAY THE PUBLIC BANK IS
STRUCTURED IS THAT IT WILL HELP TO SUPPORT EXISTING CREDIT
UNIONS AND ACTUALLY PARTNER WITH THEM, ADMINISTER THE FUNDS
THROUGH THOSE ENTITIES BECAUSE IF YOU TALK TO SMALL BUSINESSES
TODAY, IF YOU TALK TO IMMIGRANTS, IF YOU TALK TO
PEOPLE OF COLOR, IF YOU TALK TO THE UNBANKED ONE OF THE PRIMARY
CHALLENGES THAT THEY FACE IS ACCESS TO CAPITAL WAS ACCESS TO
CAPITAL TO START A BUSINESS, ACCESS TO CAPITAL TO BUY A
HOUSE, ACCESS TO CAPITAL TO LIVE DAY TO DAY, PAYCHECK TO
PAYCHECK. AND THE PROBLEM IS PREDATORY
LOANS AT HIGH INTEREST RATES THAT ARE NOT ABLE THAT IF YOU
ARE AT THE LOW INCOME OR IF YOU ARE A SMALL BUSINESS ESPECIALLY
STARTING OUT THAT IS ALL THAT IS AVAILABLE TO YOU IN THE
PRIVATE MARKETS. SO THE THE BENEFIT TO THE
OPTIONALITY TO A PUBLIC BANK TO SUPPORT OUR EXISTING CREDIT
UNION INFRASTRUCTURE IS THAT WE ALLOW FOR AN INFRASTRUCTURE
THAT CAN LOWER INTEREST RATES TO PROVIDE A PUBLIC COMPETITIVE
GOOD TO IN TURN CREATE A A MARKET THAT BENEFITS ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS. AND SO THAT'S WHY I THINK THIS
THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT IS COMMON SENSE.
IT'S ABOUT AN INVESTMENT IN OUR FUTURE CREATING THE OPTIONALITY
AND THE ECONOMIC DIVERSITY AND OPTIONS FOR THOSE WHO NEED
IT. ESPECIALLY ON AN ISSUE SUCH AS
AFFORDABILITY WHICH IS TOP OF MIND FOR EVERY SAN FRANCISCAN
AND IS NOT GOING TO GET BETTER ANYTIME SOON UNLESS WE MAKE
THOSE INVESTMENTS TODAY FOR THE SOLUTIONS THAT WE NEED
TOMORROW. AND THAT'S WHY WE WERE VOTING
IN SUPPORT OF SUPER RESOLUTION .
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT BENJAMIN.
YOU KNOW, I JUST WANT TO STATE THAT MY CONSTITUENTS ARE ASKING
ABOUT HOME LOANS. THEY ARE ASKING ABOUT BUSINESS
LOANS. THEY ARE ASKING ABOUT WAYS TO
ACCESS CAPITAL THAT ARE NOT ALWAYS AVAILABLE TO EVERYONE.
OUR CONSTITUENTS ARE ASKING FOR OPPORTUNITIES TO THRIVE.
BUSINESS OWNERS IN DEVELOPERS ARE LOOKING FOR FINANCING
AND THIS IS VERY MUCH AN ISSUE THAT HAS BEEN BROUGHT TO US BY
THE PUBLIC. SO I HOPE BEFORE ANYONE TAKES A
POSITION AGAINST THEY ACTUALLY KNOW WHAT WE'RE DOING WITH THIS
CHARTER AMENDMENT AND NOT GETTING TALKING POINTS FROM
SOMEONE THAT DOESN'T UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE ACTUALLY DOING HERE.
THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT AND WHAT IT DOES WILL ACTUALLY TAKE TIME
TO EVEN GET TO PUBLIC BANK STATUS.
THE NARRATIVE THAT A PUBLIC BANK DOES NOT ALIGN WITH THE
PRIORITIES OF SAN FRANCISCANS IS FALSE AND FABRICATED.
>> THIS IS AN IMPORTANT STEP FOR A CITY THAT HAS
HISTORICALLY BEEN ON THE FOREFRONT OF SUCCESS.
SO THE FACT THAT OTHER MUNICIPALITIES HAVE NOT BEEN
SUCCESSFUL THAT DOES NOT APPLY TO US HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. ROSE MELGAR THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT. I ALSO WANTED TO WEIGH IN IN
SUPPORT OF THIS LEGISLATION. I THINK AS MY COLLEAGUE
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD STATED, THIS IS ABOUT THE FRAMEWORK
IN MEETING THE DEADLINE THAT WE'RE UP AGAINST NOT FUNDING
AND NOT SPELLING OUT THE GOVERNANCE THAT WILL COME.
IT IS THE FRAMEWORK FOR HOW WE'RE GOING TO DO THAT AND I
FULLY SUPPORT IT. I ALSO JUST WANTED TO
UNDERSCORE THAT NOTWITHSTANDING HAVING CDF EYES AND LENDING
INSTITUTIONS THAT ARE NONPROFIT AND MANY, MANY FOR PROFIT
INSTITUTIONS IN MAY OF THIS YEAR WELLS FARGO BANK ANTLER
ENTERED A VERY LARGE SEDIMENT SETTLEMENT FOR RACIAL
DISCRIMINATION DISCRIMINATION AGAINST BLACK PEOPLE IN LENDING
PEOPLE WHO HAD PERFECTLY GOOD CREDIT SCORES AND WOULD HAVE
OTHERWISE BOUGHT HOMES WITH MORTGAGES THAT THEY COULD NOT
GET BECAUSE OF THE COLOR OF THEIR SKIN AND BECAUSE OF THAT
. YOU KNOW, WE STILL SEE GREAT
DISPARITIES IN LENDING FOR NO FINANCIAL BUSINESS REASON
AGAINST WOMEN, AGAINST PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE PROPER
DOCUMENTATION. AGAINST ALL SORTS OF HUMAN
BEINGS. THAT COULD BE THRIVING ECONOMIC
ACTORS IN OUR SOCIETY THAT WE COULD ADVANCE OUR VALUES
AND ALSO A SMART BUSINESS DECISION.
SO I THINK THAT WE ARE HEADED IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION.
I THINK SAN FRANCISCO'S ALWAYS BEEN AT THE FOREFRONT OF, YOU
KNOW, THINGS THAT PEOPLE COPY LATER.
I DO AGREE THAT WE SHOULD BE JUDICIOUS AND ALSO BE
IRRESPONSIBLE IN OUR INVESTMENT BUT I DO TOTALLY SUPPORT
AND HAVE CO-SPONSORED THIS LEGISLATION AND I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR CHEN AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR ALL THE WORK
THEY'VE DONE. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL AND THE ITEM ON THE MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEM TEN TO JULY
7TH. SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN ALL
RIGHT. MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON HIGH WALTON IRON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYE AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
EYE THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WONG VOTING
NO. >> THE TOURNAMENT IS CONTINUED
TO JULY 7TH 2026. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. >> YES IT IS NOW TIME FOR THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATION FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> AND I WOULD LIKE TO START BY
INVITING ROB REINER TO COME UP .
>> THIS IS ANOTHER BITTERSWEET ONE, FOLKS.
TODAY WE ARE PRESENTING A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO ROB
REINER, THE BUILDING MANAGER OF SAN FRANCISCO CITY HALL WHO IS
RETIRING AT THE END OF THIS WEEK AFTER MORE THAN TWO
DECADES OF SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY AS ALL OF US
FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO WORK HERE, NO CITY HALL IS MORE THAN
ANOTHER OFFICE BUILDING. IT IS A NATIONAL HISTORIC
LANDMARK A CIVIC CATHEDRAL OF UNPARALLELED BEAUTY AND THE
STAGE ON WHICH THE CITY HAS MARKED MANY OF ITS GREATEST
MOMENTS OF JOY AND GRIEF ALIKE. >> KEEPING IT STANDING,
FUNCTIONING AND WORTHY OF THE PEOPLE WE SERVE IS A
RESPONSIBILITY THAT DEMANDS BOTH TECHNICAL MASTERY
AND GENUINE COMMITMENT TO THE PUBLIC TRUST.
FOR NEARLY 17 YEARS AS BUILDING MANAGER ROB REITER HAS MET THAT
RESPONSIBILITY EVERY SINGLE DAY.
HE WAS BORN AND RAISED IN CANTON, OHIO.
AFTER EARNING A BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION
AND PUBLIC POLICY AND A JURIS DOCTOR FROM LEWIS AND CLARK LAW
SCHOOL IN PORTLAND, OREGON, HE MOVED TO THE BAY WORKING
IN COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE AND HIGH RISE BUILDING
MANAGEMENT. >> HE CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO
CITY GOVERNMENT AFTER SPOTTING A REAL PROPERTY OFFICER JOB
POSTING AT THE SFP YOU SEE ON CRAIGSLIST.
>> HE APPLIED, GOT THE JOB AND SERVED IN THAT ROLE FROM
2004 TO 2009 WHEN THEN DIRECTOR OF REAL ESTATE AMY BROWN
ENCOURAGED HIM TO APPLY FOR THE CITY HALL CITY HALL BUILDING
MANAGER POSITION. HE HAS HELD IT EVER SINCE.
ON ANY GIVEN DAY ROB ASSIST ASSISTS STAFF FROM OUR CITY
DEPARTMENTS WITH THE DAILY LOGISTICS OF LIFE IN THIS
BUILDING AND WORKS CLOSELY WITH THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE TO KEEP US
SAFE AND SECURE. HE COLLABORATES WITH THE CITY
HALL PRESERVATION ADVISORY COMMISSION TO SAFEGUARD THE
BUILDINGS HISTORIC INTEGRITY INCLUDING OVERSEEING THE
APPLICATION OF THE TUNA MAC COATING THAT GIVES THE DOME ITS
ICONIC GOLD APPEARANCE. ROB HAS NEVER SOUGHT THE
SPOTLIGHT BUT HIS ACCOMPLISHMENTS SPEAK FOR
THEMSELVES. HE LED THE EFFORT THAT EARNED
CITY HALL LEED PLATINUM CERTIFICATION IN 2015 A
DESIGNATION FROM THE U.S. GREEN BUILDING COUNCIL RECOGNIZED THE
HIGHEST STANDARD OF ENERGY AND ENVIRONMENTAL PERFORMANCE.
MAKING CITY HALL THE OLDEST BUILDING IN THE UNITED STATES
TO RECEIVE IT, HE OVERSAW THE INSTALLATION OF THE DYNAMIC
EXTERIOR LIGHTING SYSTEM THAT EACH NIGHT TRANSFORMS THE
BUILDING'S BUILDING'S FACADE INTO A LIVING EXPRESSION OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S VALUES AND CELEBRATIONS.
>> SERVING UNDER FIVE MAYORS, HE'S MANAGED CITY HALL THROUGH
EVENTS OF LOCAL NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL SIGNIFICANCE.
>> MANY OF US WILL REMEMBER ROB MOST FOR THE COUNTLESS BUILDING
TOURS HE HAS PROVIDED TO MAYORS VISITING DIGNITARIES,
SUPERVISORS, STAFF AND VISITORS.
HE HAS A WEALTH OF KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THIS BUILDING ITS
ARCHITECTURE, ITS HISTORY AND ALL THE STORIES EMBEDDED
IN EVERY BEAM AND SCULPTURE AND INSCRIPTION.
>> ALL OF US WHO'VE MADE THE TRIP UP TO THE DOME TO THE TOP
OF THE DOME WITH HIM KNOW THAT HE PERFORMS HIS DUTIES WITH THE
ENTHUSIASM OF SOMEONE WHO NEVER STOPPED BEING HONORED BY THIS
PLACE. >> ROB AMY BROWN WAS RIGHT
AND SAN FRANCISCO IS BETTER FOR THE YEARS YOU HAVE GIVEN US ON
BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE, CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR
RETIREMENT AND EXTEND OUR GRATITUDE AND CONGRATULATIONS
TO YOUR FAMILY, YOUR WIFE DEBORAH, YOUR SONS NOAH,
BENJAMIN AND MATEO. YOUR GRANDDAUGHTER DANNY
AND YOUR PARENTS PAULA AND JOHN .
AS YOU START THIS NEXT CHAPTER OF YOUR LIFE, KNOW THAT THE
FOLKS HERE ARE GOING TO MISS YOU VERY, VERY MUCH.
>> AND AS EVIDENCE OF THAT, THEY'RE ALREADY PUTTING
THEMSELVES IN THE QUEUE. I'M GOING TO LET MY COLLEAGUES
SPEAK FIRST AND THEN SALLY ORTH, THE DIRECTOR OF REAL
ESTATE ALSO WANTS TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT BENJAMIN ROB, I JUST
WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR RESPONSIVENESS, FOR YOUR
SERVICE BUT MOSTLY FOR ALWAYS MAKING SURE THAT ANY REQUEST
WAS ADDRESSED IN A TIMELY MANNER.
YOU REALLY DO GET THINGS DONE SO THAT WE CAN OPERATE
SEAMLESSLY. >> AND SO I WANT TO MAKE SURE
THAT YOU KNOW THAT I APPRECIATE YOU.
MY ENTIRE OFFICE APPRECIATES YOU AND CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR
RETIREMENT. >> SUPER VISOR.
DORSEY THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN RABBI, YOU KNOW YOU
ARE ONE OF THE PEOPLE WHO THERE'S A HANDFUL OF PEOPLE WHO
I RECOGNIZE WHO JUST OVER THE YEARS IT'S A REMINDER OF HOW
LONG I'VE WORKED IN THIS BUILDING AND HOW MUCH I HAVE
CONFIDENCE AND TRUST AND JUST THE PROFESSIONALISM OF PEOPLE
WHO SERVE THIS BUILDING AND I SHARE YOUR LOVE AND ALL OF THIS
BUILDING HAVING WORKED HERE FOR SO LONG AND CONGRATULATIONS ON
YOUR RETIREMENT, I WILL MISS YOU.
>> SALLY OR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND GOOD AFTERNOON
BOARD MEMBERS. SO I JUST WANTED TO SAY A FEW
WORDS ON BEHALF OF THE REAL ESTATE DIVISION AND WE WANTED
TO EXTEND OUR APPRECIATION TO ROB FOR HIS MANY YEARS OF
SERVICE AS CITY HALL'S BUILDING MANAGER.
HIS DEDICATION HAS ALWAYS BEEN ROOTED IN ONE THING THE PEOPLE
WHO WORK AND RELY ON THIS BUILDING ARE HIS TOP PRIORITY
WHETHER IT WAS SUPPORTING ELECTED OFFICIALS OR TENANT
DEPARTMENTS, BUILDING STAFF OR THE MANY VISITORS WHO COME TO
THIS HISTORIC LANDMARK EVERY DAY.
ROB APPROACHED EACH REQUEST WITH PATIENCE, PRIDE AND A
SINCERE DESIRE TO SOLVE PROBLEMS.
>> AND IMPORTANTLY HE UNDERSTOOD THAT CITY HALL IS
NOT JUST A LANDMARK IT'S A WORKPLACE BUT IT'S ALSO A
COMMUNITY. AND HE GENUINELY WANTED TO DO
HIS BEST FOR EVERYONE WHO WALKED THROUGH THESE HALLOWED
HALLS. >> SO ROB, THANK YOU FOR YOUR
STEADY COMMITMENT AND THE CARE THAT YOU BROUGHT TO THIS
BUILDING AND TO THE PEOPLE WHO VISIT IT EVERY DAY.
>> SO WE'RE GRATEFUL FOR ALL YOU'VE DONE AND WE LOOK FORWARD
TO CELEBRATING WITH YOU LATER TODAY.
>> AND WE WISH YOU ALL THE BEST IN YOUR WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT
. >> ROB REINER THE FLOOR IS
YOURS. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MELMAN
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. I THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THE
COMMENDATION AND FOR YOUR RECOGNITION TODAY.
IT HAS BEEN AN HONOR TO SPEND THE LAST 22 YEARS SERVING THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO BOTH DURING MY EARLY
YEARS WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION
AND FOR THE PAST 17 YEARS AS BUILDING MANAGER OF CITY HALL.
WHILE MANAGING OUR CIVIC FACILITIES HAS BEEN A REWARDING
RESPONSIBILITY THE MOST MEANINGFUL PART MY CAREER HAS
BEEN SERVING THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND WORKING
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE DEDICATED TEAMS ACROSS OUR CITY
GOVERNMENT AND AMONGST THAT DEDICATED TEAM.
I WOULD BE REMISS IF I DIDN'T THINK MY STAFF LAURIE MAZOLA,
ERIC NELSON AND HOWARD WONG IN OUR WHOLE LABOR TEAM.
I COULDN'T HAVE DONE IT WITHOUT THEM.
IT IS TRULY A TEAM EFFORT. I WANTED TO AGAIN THANK YOU FOR
THIS HONOR FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND FOR THIS MEMORABLE SEND OFF
AS I BEGIN MY RETIREMENT. >> THANK YOU.
>> YOU YOU BET YOU. SHE'S GOING AWAY.
SORRY. LANGUAGE CAME OFF THE TONE WITH
THE BLACK HAIR. YEAH, HE DOES HIS HAIR.
HIS HAIR LOOKS JUST IT'S PRETTY CUTE.
HE'S A CLOWN. MAYBE TALLER.
>> NEXT UP DISTRICT TO SURPRISE CHERYL.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. MANDEL, MINN.
>> THERE ARE COLLEAGUES TO CLOSE OUT PRIDE MONTH.
IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE LLOYD HADDAD AND KEITH WICKER.
LLOYD AND KEITH, WILL YOU PLEASE COME UP TO THE LECTERN?
NOW LLOYD AND KEITH ARE THE OWNERS OF TWO.
>> WELL, REALLY THREE BUT TWO THREE SITES, TWO BUSINESSES,
BUSINESSES FOUR SHOT FOUR. >> SO TWO BUSINESSES, FOUR
SITES. AND NOT ONLY AM I LUCKY TO CALL
THEM THEIR BUSINESS CONSTITUENTS, I'M LUCKY TO CALL
MYSELF A CUSTOMER. AS THE OWNERS OF CAPRICORN
FRAMING AND WALTER ADAMS FRAMING, IT IS MY HONOR TO
COMMEND YOU BOTH FOR YOUR BUSINESS LEADERSHIP, YOUR
PHILANTHROPY, YOUR CIVIC ENGAGEMENT AND JUST OVERALL
SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO. >> NOW LLOYD IS ORIGINALLY FROM
EL PASO, TEXAS AND KEITH IS ORIGINALLY FROM BALTIMORE,
MARYLAND AND BOTH FOUND THEIR WAY TO SAN FRANCISCO LLOYD
IN 1999 AND KEITH IN 2005 WHERE THEY BUILT A LIFE AND A
BUSINESS TOGETHER. LLOYD FOUNDED CAPRICORN FRAMING
IN 2006, BRINGING AN ENGINEERING BACKGROUND THAT
SHAPED THE SHOP'S PRECISION FOCUSED, CONSERVATION DRIVEN
APPROACH TO CUSTOM FRAMING. NOW KEITH JOINED THE BUSINESS
IN 2014, ADDING HIS OWN BACKGROUND IN AERONAUTICAL
ENGINEERING WOODWORKING AND AVIATION.
HE'S A RETIRED ARMY HELICOPTER PILOT INSTRUCTOR AND A FORMER
KTVU CHANNEL TWO NEWS PILOT. TOGETHER LLOYD AND KEITH HAVE
BUILT CAPRICORN INTO ONE OF THE BAY AREA'S LEADING CONSERVATION
FRAMING STUDIOS. WORKING WITH ARTISTS,
COLLECTORS, INTERIOR DESIGNERS AND FAMILIES ON EVERYTHING FROM
ARCHIVAL MOUNTING TO COMPLEX SHADOW BOX DESIGN IN 2023 THEY
EXPANDED THEIR WORK THROUGH SHARED OWNERSHIP OF WALTER
ADAMS FRAMING NOW A LEGACY BUSINESS GROWING THEIR
FOOTPRINT TO ADDITIONAL LOCATIONS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO
WHILE HOLDING TO THE SAME PRESERVATION STANDARD LLOYD'S
CAPRICORN WAS BUILT ON. THEY RECENTLY OPENED A NEW
PRODUCTION FACILITY TO SUPPORT THAT GROWTH.
NOW THIS YEAR ALSO MARKS CAPRICORN FRAMINGS 20TH
ANNIVERSARY TWO DECADES OF CRAFTSMANSHIP INNOVATION
AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND WHEN I WENT TO CAPRICORN AND MET WITH YOU, LLOYD, TO
PRESENT THE CERTIFICATE OF HONOR FOR THAT ANNIVERSARY I
FELT SO WELCOME TO BE IN YOUR SPACE BUT ALSO TO BE IN YOUR
BRAIN AS YOU EXPLAINED TO ME THE INTRICACIES OF CUSTOM
FRAMING AND THE CARE AND THE THOUGHT THAT YOU PUT INTO EVERY
WORK OF ART AND BY THAT I DON'T MEAN WHAT'S INSIDE THE FRAME.
I MEAN THE FRAME. >> I ALSO LEARNED THAT YOU TO
SEE YOUR NEIGHBORING FRINGE SHOPS NOT AS COMPETITION BUT
RATHER PEERS. TRULY A TESTAMENT TO YOUR
BUSINESS VALUE OF SUPPORTING COMMUNITY THAT REALLY WILL
STICK WITH ME WHEN SOMEONE COMES IN WHO WOULD BE A BETTER
CUSTOMER FOR THE FRAME SHOP DOWN THE STREET WE SEND THEM
THERE AND THEY DO BACK AND FORTH.
THAT ATTITUDE IS WHAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO FABULOUS.
AND THANK YOU LLOYD AND KEITH OF IT LONG EXTENDED THAT
CRAFTSMANSHIP INTO PHILANTHROPY SUPPORTING ORGANIZATIONS
INCLUDING ART FOR AIDS SOUTHERN EXPOSURE, THE DENALI FOUNDATION
AND CREATIVITY EXPLORED ALONG WITH GROUPS ADVANCING MENTAL
HEALTH, WELLNESS EQUITY AND LGBTQ TWO PLUS L G B T Q
PLUS VISIBILITY. KEITH THE MILITARY VETERAN HAS
ALSO MADE SUPPORT FOR FELLOW VETERANS CENTRAL TO THE
COUPLE'S GIVING. CARRYING FORWARD THE SAME
VALUES OF TEAMWORK AND LOOKING AFTER THE PEOPLE BESIDE YOU
THAT HE LEARNED IN SERVICE. LLOYD KEITH YOUR PERSONAL
AND PROFESSIONAL PARTNERSHIP CHIP HAS BEEN DEFINED BY
INCLUSION GENEROSITY AND A COMMITMENT TO GIVING BACK TO
THIS CITY. AND ON A PERSONAL NOTE.
I ALSO WANT TO CONGRATULATE YOU TOO WHO I HAVE LEARNED WILL BE
GETTING MARRIED IN SEPTEMBER IN THE PRESIDIO.
I'M SO EXCITED FOR BOTH OF YOU FOR THIS CELEBRATION OF YOUR
LOVE AND FRANKLY ELATED YOUR CHOOSING TO TIE THE KNOT
IN DISTRICT TWO. >> BUT IN ALL SERIOUSNESS, ON
BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THANK YOU BOTH FOR
EVERYTHING YOU'VE GIVEN TO THE CITY'S ARTISTS, TO THE BUSINESS
AND TO THE COMMUNITY. CONGRATULATIONS ON THIS HONOR
AND HELPING US CLOSE OUT PRIDE MONTH HERE AT CITY HALL.
>> THANK YOU. >> HEY, SOMETHING SOMETHING.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE KIND WORDS.
WHEN WE STARTED OUR BUSINESS ONE OF THE THINGS THAT WE
WANTED TO BRING WAS THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHICH IS SO STRONG. >> AND LIKE YOU SAID, WE VIEW
MANY OF OUR BUSINESSES AROUND US AS PEERS, NOT COMPETITORS.
AND THE ATTITUDE OF SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS FOSTERED
THAT KIND OF FEELING. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THE
COMMENDATION. WE'RE VERY EXCITED TO GET
MARRIED AFTER 13 YEARS. >> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THIS IS REALLY A VERY GREAT HONOR.
WE WERE VERY PLEASED TO GET THE ANNOUNCEMENT AND AND SURPRISED
AND WE WILL DO OUR BEST TO CONTINUE TO UPHOLD THE STRONG
FEELINGS OF SMALL BUSINESS SUPPORT AND THE LGBTQ COMMUNITY
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. THANK
DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR WONG. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE THE VETS
SUPPORTING COULD YOU COME UP? >> I WANT TO RECOGNIZE VETS
SUPPORTING IN HONOR OF PTSD AWARENESS MONTH AND THEIR
IMPORTANT WORK SERVING VETERANS AND THEIR FAMILIES IN OUR
COMMUNITY. FOR MANY YEAR FOR MANY VETERANS
RETURNING HOME FROM ACTIVE DUTY IS NOT A SIMPLE TRANSITION.
THE STRUCTURE, SHARED MISSION AND STRONG BONDS OF MILITARY
SERVICE CAN BE DIFFICULT TO REPLACE.
VETERANS MAY FIND THEMSELVES NAVIGATING BENEFITS, NEW
CAREERS, FAMILY LIFE AND PERSONAL GOALS WITHOUT THE
FAMILIAR SUPPORT SYSTEM THEY ONCE HAD.
THAT SUPPORTING WAS FOUNDED TO HELP VETERANS THROUGH THE
CHALLENGES OF TRANSITIONING FROM MILITARY SERVICE TO
CIVILIAN LIFE. THE WORK BEGAN BY PROVIDING
PEER SUPPORT TO VETERANS PARTICIPATING IN SAN
FRANCISCO'S VETERANS JUSTICE COURT.
AND TODAY THEY CONTINUE SERVING AS A HUB CONNECTING VETERANS
AND FAMILIES TO COMMUNITY RESOURCES AND THROUGH THE
VETERANS ADMINISTRATION THROUGH MENTORSHIP, SOCIAL
RE-ENGAGEMENT, EDUCATION AROUND EARNED BENEFITS AND PEER
SUPPORT THAT SUPPORTING HELPS VETERANS REBUILD POSITIVE
SOCIAL STRUCTURE, DEVELOP HEALTHY ROUTINES AND REDUCE
ISOLATION. THE WORK CARRIES FORWARD THE
SPIRIT OF THE BATTLE BUDDY SYSTEM MAKING SURE NO VETERAN
FEELS LEFT BEHIND. I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE JASON
CHITTAGONG, THE PRESIDENT AND FOUNDER OF THAT'S
SUPPORTING A MARINE VETERAN AND A PAST COMMISSIONER ON THE
SAN FRANCISCO VETERANS AFFAIRS COMMISSION.
JASON'S SERVICE SPANS ADVOCACY, WELLNESS, HOUSING AND VETERAN
FOCUSED PROGRAMS AND THROUGH VETS SUPPORTING OR SELLING
INITIATIVES HE HELPS CREATE OPPORTUNITIES FOR COMMODITY
HEALING AND RENEWED PURPOSE. THAT SAME SPIRIT IS REFLECTED
IN VETS SUPPORTING THIS PARTNERSHIP WITH WOODEN BOATS
FOR VETERANS WHICH USES SAILING RESTORATION, TEAMWORK
AND SHARED PURPOSE TO HELP VETERANS AND THEIR FAMILIES
RECONNECT, BUILD SKILLS AND REDISCOVER INNER STRENGTH.
AND I WANT TO THANK WILL CUEVAS WHO SERVES AS THE CHIEF
FINANCIAL OFFICER AND ON THE BOARD OF GOVERNORS FOR VETS
SUPPORTING WILL SERVE IN THE MARINE CORPS AND IS VERY
PASSIONATE ABOUT CONTINUING PUBLIC SERVICE FOR VETERANS
IN OUR COMMUNITY. HIS DEDICATION IS A REMINDER
THAT SERVICE DOES NOT END WHEN THE UNIFORM COMES OFF.
AND IN HONOR OF PTSD AWARENESS MONTH WE COMMEND VETS
SUPPORTING JASON WILL AND ALL THOSE WORKING TO HELP VETERANS
FIND SUPPORT, PURPOSE, HEALING AND COMMUNITY AFTER SERVICE.
>> WE'D LIKE TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
YES, WE DO APPRECIATE RECOGNIZING PTSD MONTH.
WE ALL ACTUALLY MET AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE POST OUR
MILITARY SERVICE. WE DECIDED TO USE OUR BENEFITS
AND ATTEND COLLEGE. >> THERE WAS A NEED FOR A
COMMUNITY. THERE WAS A NEED FOR OUTREACH.
FOR THOSE OF US TRANSITIONING PARTICULARLY THOSE OF US THAT
COME FROM A COMBAT BACKGROUND JASON MYSELF OR OTHER MEMBERS
SEAN SCHAAF AND NICHOLAS ROUSSIMOFF WHO'S HERE ALL
BONDED WITHIN THIS VETS AS IF AS YOU ORGANIZATION POST OUR
COLLEGE CAREER WE DECIDED TO CONTINUE THIS SERVICE TO THE
COMMUNITY. AND WE JUST REALLY APPRECIATE
IT BECAUSE PTSD DOESN'T ALWAYS HAVE A FACE.
COULD YOU HIDE BEHIND A SMILE AND BALANCE WORK LIFE BALANCE?
COULD HIDE BEHIND CRYING A LOT OF THINGS.
AND THE FACT THAT WE'RE RECOGNIZING THIS WE ARE GREATLY
APPRECIATIVE TO SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND SUPERVISOR HUANG THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> I JUST WANT TO QUICKLY THANK ALL THE SUPPORT GROUP HERE
SURPRISE ANYONE AND BOARD SUPERVISORS AND MY FOUNDATION
OF SUPPORT GROUP. >> JENNY PEREZ AND NICHOLAS
WERE SOME OF DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN. COLLEAGUES AS WE CLOSE OUT
PRIDE MONTH TODAY I AM HONORING A REMARKABLE YOUNG LEADER OUR
OUTGOING DISTRICT SIX YOUTH COMMISSIONER GABBY LA STANA.
>> GABBY WAS BORN AND RAISED IN THE TENDERLOIN AND NOW LIVES
IN THE SOUTH OF MARKET NEIGHBORHOOD.
SHE ATTENDED THE PRESIDIO KNOLLS SCHOOL IN SOMA BEFORE
GOING ON TO SACRED HEART CATHEDRAL PREPARATORY.
SHE GREW UP IN A FAMILY OF ORGANIZERS.
THE KIND OF HOUSEHOLD WHERE YOU LEARN EARLY THAT YOU DON'T JUST
COMPLAIN ABOUT PROBLEMS. YOU SHOW UP AND YOU DO THE WORK
TO FIX THEM AND THAT'S A LESSON THAT CLEARLY STUCK.
>> FORMER SUPERVISOR MATT HANEY FIRST APPOINTED HER TO THE
YOUTH COMMISSION WHEN SHE WAS JUST 12 YEARS OLD AND BY THE
TIME I HAD THE CHANCE TO MAKE MY APPOINTMENT TO THE YOUTH
COMMISSION, GABBY'S REAPPOINTMENT WAS A NO BRAINER.
SHE HAS NOW FINISHED HER SIXTH TERM ON THE YOUTH COMMISSION
AND SHE HAS SERVED AS ITS CHAIR.
WHAT STRIKES ME MOST ABOUT GABBY'S WORK IS HOW PERSONAL IT
IS TO HER. SHE ORGANIZED THE LGBTQ PLUS
TASK FORCE BECAUSE SHE UNDERSTOOD WHAT WAS AT STAKE
FOR YOUTH IN OUR SCHOOLS IN A SCARY AND UNCERTAIN TIME WITH
ONGOING SETBACKS TO OUR RIGHTS AS WE SAW EVEN JUST THIS
MORNING WITH THE US SUPREME COURT'S DECISION ON TRANS
INCLUSION IN SPORTS. GABBY FOUGHT FOR SAN
FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ TWO A PLUS COALITION ON SAFETY FUNDING.
SHE PUSHED TO CREATE REAL SAFE SPACES FOR LGBTQ PLUS YOUTH
AND SHE WORKED TO GET BETTER, MORE HONEST HEALTH CURRICULUM
IN THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT'S CLASSROOMS.
SHE LEADS WITH STRONG CONVICTION AND PUTS HER WHOLE
HEART INTO HER WORK. IN FACT, SHE HAS SHOWN THAT
SAME HEART AND CONVICTION IN EVERYTHING THAT I HAVE SEEN
HER TAKE ON. SHE CHAMPIONED VIETNAMESE LIGHT
LANGUAGE ACCESS ACROSS CITY DEPARTMENTS.
SHE LED THE CHARGE TO RESTORE LEGAL SERVICES FOR IMMIGRANT
FAMILIES. SHE HAS BEEN A STRONG VOICE FOR
NEEDED RESOURCES IN THE FILIPINO COMMUNITY.
SHE WAS CHOSEN AS ONE OF ONLY TWO CALIFORNIA DELEGATES TO THE
U.S. SENATE YOUTH PROGRAM AND SHE CO-FOUNDED THE YOUNG
LEADERS IN CLIMATE ACTION. HER OUTSTANDING CIVIC
ACHIEVEMENTS TOGETHER WITH HER EQUALLY IMPRESSIVE ACADEMIC
RECORD APPARENTLY EARNED HER A SPOT AT A SCHOOL.
SOME OF YOU MAY HAVE HEARD OF HARVARD UNIVERSITY, WHICH SHE
WILL BEGIN ATTENDING THIS FALL TO STUDY ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE
AND PUBLIC POLICY. AS WE HONOR GABBY FOR ALL HER
CIVIC ACCOMPLISHMENTS TODAY, I THINK ABOUT THE REMARKABLE
EXAMPLE SHE HAS SET. SOMEONE WHO STARTED AT THE AGE
OF 12 STUCK WITH IT AND TURNED THAT COMMITMENT TO REAL CHANGE
FOR THE COMMUNITIES SHE CARES ABOUT.
THAT KIND OF EXAMPLE DOESN'T JUST INSPIRE ADMIRATION, IT
INSPIRES ACTION. SHE HAS SHOWN AN ENTIRE
GENERATION OF THE YOUNG SAN FRANCISCANS WHO KNOW HER HOW
MUCH CAN BE POSSIBLE WHEN YOU TAKE CIVIC ENGAGEMENT SERIOUSLY
. AND TODAY OUR CITY IS BETTER
FOR IT. AS SHE HEADS OFF TO HARVARD I
KNOW I SPEAK FOR SO MANY OF THE SAN FRANCISCANS WHO'VE KNOWN
AND HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK WITH HER.
SHE WILL BE DEEPLY MISSED. OUR CITY WILL FEEL HER ABSENCE
WHETHER SHE KNOW THEY KNOW HER OR NOT.
BUT I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT GABBY WILL CARRY EVERYTHING SHE'S
LEARNED OUT INTO THE WORLD AND CONTINUE TO MAKE US PROUD.
KNOWING THIS ISN'T A GOODBYE FROM SAN FRANCISCO BUT THE
BEGINNING OF A NEXT CHAPTER. GABBY, WE THANK YOU FOR ALL OF
YOUR SERVICE TO OUR CITY. WE WISH YOU THE VERY BEST
IN YOUR ENDEAVORS TO COME. AND WE'RE EXCITED TO SEE ALL
THE WAYS YOU'RE GOING TO CONTINUE TO MAKE US PROUD BY
MAKING A DIFFERENCE. CONGRATULATIONS.
AND BEFORE WE HEAR FROM GABBY, I KNOW WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM
JOYCE ON BUT I BELIEVE I HAVE A COLLEAGUE WHO ALSO WANTS TO SAY
SOMETHING. >> SO LET ME HAND IT OFF IF I
MAY. SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU.
FIRST I JUST WANTED TO SAY. SUPERVISOR DORSEY, THIS IS AN
OUTSTANDING CHOICE FOR RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATION.
SO GABBY WORKING TO MISS YOU. I AT THE RISK OF EMBARRASSING
YOU FURTHER YOU ARE ONE OF OUR LONGEST SERVING YOUTH
COMMISSIONERS EVER IN WHAT AN OUTSTANDING YOUTH COMMISSIONER
YOU HAVE BEEN. IN ADDITION TO ALL THE THINGS
THAT MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR DORSEY LISTED IN TERMS OF YOUR
ACHIEVEMENT I JUST WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE WHAT A MENTOR
AND LEADER YOU HAVE BEEN FOR OTHERS IN THE YOUTH COMMISSION
IN ALL THE DISTRICT YOUTH COUNCILS YOU HAVE BEEN JUST A
BEACON OF LEADERSHIP AND FORTHRIGHTNESS.
YOU HAVE LED THE WAY ON SO MANY DIFFERENT ISSUES AND YOU HAVE
BEEN THAT SORT OF MORAL COMPASS FOR SO MANY.
AND I ALSO WANT TO SAY A SUPERVISOR DORSEY WE DO
RECOGNIZE YOUNG PEOPLE IN KNOTS IN THIS CHAMBER SO I'M REALLY
GLAD WE'RE DOING THIS TODAY AND THAT WE'RE RECOGNIZING
GABBY FOR HER OUTSTANDING CONTRIBUTIONS TO LEADERSHIP
AND TO HAVING YOUTH VOICE IN OUR CITY.
I ALSO WANT TO PUT IN A GOOD WORD FOR FOR JOY AND THE STAFF
AT THE YOUTH COMMISSION FOR ALL OF THE WORK THAT THEY DO
AND FOR SUPPORTING GABBY AND THE OTHER YOUTH
COMMISSIONERS IN MAKING SURE THAT WE ARE HEARING THEIR VOICE
AND TAKING THEIR PERSPECTIVE INTO ACCOUNT WHEN WE MAKE
DECISIONS. SO AGAIN, GABBY AND I CANNOT
WAIT TO SEE WHAT HAPPENS WHEN YOU COME BACK TO SAN FRANCISCO
AFTER COLLEGE AND WHAT YOU'RE GOING TO DO.
I KNOW WHATEVER IT IS THAT YOU TAKE ON YOU WILL BE AWESOME AT
IT. YOU'LL BE A ROCK STAR AND I
THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE FOR OUR CITY SO FAR.
SO FAR BECAUSE I KNOW YOU'RE GOING TO COME BACK AND DO
AMAZING THINGS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. I WILL JUST ADD MY OWN
CONGRATULATIONS. GABBY, IT'S BEEN GREAT TO WORK
WITH YOU AND INVITE UP JOY'S JOY REALLY QUICKLY TO THANK YOU
SUPERVISORS FOR RECOGNIZING OUR CHAIR GABBY LEZAMA.
SHE'S BEEN WONDERFUL. WE HAVE RECORD BREAKING
APPLICANTS 156 APPLICANTS THIS SEASON AND SO MANY OF THEM
QUOTE GABBY AS AN INSPIRATION AS TO WHY THEY'RE BEING
CIVICALLY ENGAGED AND THEY WANT TO APPLY TO THE YOUTH
COMMISSION AND THE YOUTH COMMISSION.
THESE SIX YEARS HAVE BEEN A THIRD OF OUR LIFETIME NAME
AND I KNOW SHE'S GOING TO COME BACK INTO THIS BUILDING AND TO
CONTINUE TO ADVOCATE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE AND HER COMMUNITIES.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH JOY FOR
THE KIND WORDS AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THIS
INCREDIBLE HONOR AND FOR YOUR STEADFAST SUPPORT FOR SAN
FRANCISCO'S YOUTH ALONG WITH THE AMAZING KIND WORDS
AND SUPERVISORS MEAGHAN RANDLEMAN AS A COMMISSIONER
AND CHAIR OF THIS FRANCISCO YOUTH COMMISSION I AM
ESPECIALLY HONORED TO ACCEPT THIS COMMENDATION AT THE TAIL
END OF PRIDE MONTH. >> PRIDE HAS ALWAYS BEEN
DEFINED BY RESISTANCE FROM THE COMPTON CAFETERIA RIOTS IN THE
TENDERLOIN TO THE CURRENT FIGHT AGAINST ANTI AND ANTI-TRANS
LEGISLATION ACROSS THE NATION. AND I LIKE TO THINK THAT MY
COMMISSIONERS AND I HAVE BROUGHT THAT SAME GRIT TO THE
FIGHT FOR THIS CITY'S YOUTH. >> ONE OF MY PROUDEST
ACCOMPLISHMENTS THAT WAS MENTIONED EARLIER ON THE
COMMISSION WAS REESTABLISHING THE LGBTQ PLUS TASK FORCE
IN 2023. THROUGH OUR WORK WE WERE ABLE
TO ADVOCATE FOR SAFER CONDITIONS IN SHELTERS FOR
AND TRANS YOUTH AND FUNDING THE SAFETY INITIATIVES OF SERVING
YOUTH ORGANIZATIONS. >> MOST IMPORTANTLY, HOWEVER,
AT LEAST FOR ME WE WERE ALSO ABLE TO SHOW THAT YOUNG VOICES
DESERVE A SEA OF THE DECISION MAKING TABLE.
SO I WOULD LIKE TO THANK THE DISTRICT SIX OFFICE FOR
GENUINELY BELIEVING IN ME AND REAPPOINTING ME THREE TIMES
AND ALSO JUST SUPPORTING OUR ADVOCACY FOR DX SIX YOUTH THE
ENTIRE TIME YOU HAVE BEEN IN OFFICE.
>> I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK MY FELLOW YOUTH COMMISSIONERS
FOR THEIR UNWAVERING DEDICATION TO THIS CITY AND MY YOUTH
COMMISSION STAFF JOYCE AND JOSHUA RUDY OCHOA
AND FORMER DIRECTOR ALONDRA ESQUIVEL GARCIA FOR BEING
INCREDIBLE MENTORS WHO HAVE TRULY CHANGED THE TRAJECTORY OF
MY LIFE AND TEACHING ME HOW TO SERVE MY COMMUNITY ALSO THANK
YOU TO THE AMAZING COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS AND ADVOCATES WHO
HAVE SUPPORTED OUR MISSION FOR THE PAST 30 YEARS.
>> LASTLY, THANK YOU TO MY FAMILY AND FRIENDS FOR ALWAYS
SUPPORTING ME. I CANNOT WAIT TO SEE MORE
DIVERSE YOUNG VOICES IN CITY HALL.
>> THANK YOU AGAIN
. >> ALL RIGHT WITH THAT MADAM
CLERK, LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM 11 ITEM 11 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY,
JUNE 29TH, 2026 AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE
REPORT ITEM 11 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ADD THE
COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME ART AGNUS WAY TO THE 500 AND THE
600 BLOCK OF CONNECTICUT STREET AND RECOGNITION OF FORMER
MAYOR ART AGNUS FOR HIS DECADES OF DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVICE
AND COMMITMENT TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL IN THIS ITEM ON ITEM 11 SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 12 ITEM 12 THIS ITEM WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY JUNE 29TH
AND WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION AS A COMMITTEE
REPORT. ITEM 12 IS A MOTION TO AMEND
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS RULES OF ORDER BY AMENDING RULE 1.3.3
IN-PERSON AND REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT TO CONFORM THE RULE
WITH THE PUBLIC COMMENT CHANGES TO ADD A NEW RULE 1.3.4 REMOTE
PUBLIC COMMENT DISRUPTION POLICY TO ADOPT A POLICY FOR
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO HANDLE DISRUPTIONS TO REMOTE
PUBLIC PARTICIPATION ADDING A NEW RULE 1.3.5 DISORDERLY
CONDUCT BY PUBLIC COMMENTERS TO CLARIFY THE PROCEDURES AROUND
DISORDERLY CONDUCT BY PUBLIC COMMENTERS AND TO AMEND RULE
3.8 PUBLIC COMMENT AT COMMITTEE MEETINGS TO PROHIBIT COMMITTEES
FROM LIMITING THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF TIME FOR PUBLIC COMMENT ON
AN ITEM. CHAIR WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH
PRESIDENT MADAM AND COLLEAGUES YOU MAY SEE THAT THIS WAS
FORWARD HERE WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION.
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT IS BEING FORCED UPON US FROM THE STATE
LEGISLATURE TO TAKE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT.
SOME OF YOU MAY REMEMBER THAT AND BY THE WAY, I AM 100%
AND PROVIDING ACCESS TO THE PUBLIC.
BUT SOME OF YOU MAY REMEMBER THAT DURING THE PANDEMIC WE HAD
TO SIT HERE FOR HOURS, SOMETIMES TWO TWO IN THE
MORNING AND LISTEN TO PEOPLE CALL IN THAT WERE NOT
CONSTITUENTS THAT WERE FROM OTHER STATES AND FROM OTHER
COUNTRIES AND ONE I CERTAINLY BELIEVE THAT IF WE CANNOT
RECEIVE DONATIONS AND SUPPORT FROM PEOPLE FROM OTHER
COUNTRIES, WE SHOULD NOT HAVE TO SIT HERE AND LISTEN TO THEM
TALK ABOUT THE BUSINESS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND THIS HAS BEEN
BROUGHT TO US WITHOUT THE OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO SET RULES
AND WAYS THAT WE CAN DO THIS TO MAKE SURE THAT IT IS FOR OUR
CONSTITUENTS AND FOLKS WHO HAVE A REAL REASON TO CALL IN TO A
BOARD MEETING. AND SO DEFINITELY NOT
SUPPORTIVE OF THIS. THE STATE LEGISLATURE DOES NOT
EVEN TAKE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THEIR MEETINGS SO HOW CAN
WE BE FORCED TO DO SOMETHING THAT THEY DON'T EVEN DO IT JUST
BEHOOVES ME. SO I WANTED TO LET YOU KNOW WHY
I CAME WITH OUR RECOMMENDATION AND I THINK IT'S TERRIBLE THAT
THIS IS BEING FORCED UPON US. CHERYL I CAN'T AGREE WITH MY
COLLEAGUE'S REMARKS MORE 100% UP AND DOWN THE LINE.
I AGREE WITH YOU IF I DIDN'T THINK THIS WOULD COST US MONEY
ON THE INEVITABLE LAWSUIT I WOULD VOTE AGAINST IT JUST I
PROBABLY CAN'T SAY WHAT I WANTED TO SAY THERE BUT IT'S
HYPOCRISY EXACTLY LIKE YOU SAID.
>> CHAIR WALTON. AND QUITE FRANKLY I THINK THIS
IS GOING TO NOT INCREASE PUBLIC PARTICIPATION.
I THINK THIS IS GOING TO END UP BACKFIRING AND DECREASING
PUBLIC PARTICIPATION FOR THE REGULAR PEOPLE WHO HAVE LIVES
AND JOBS AND CHILDREN AND OBLIGATIONS AND ARE JUST
TRYING TO WEIGH IN ON THE CITY THAT THEY LIVE IN TO MAKE THEIR
LIVES BETTER AND TO HELP EVERYBODY ELSE, THEY'RE GOING
TO GET PUSHED OUT BY ALL THE WACKADOO THOSE AROUND THE WORLD
WHO DECIDE TO OPINE BECAUSE THEY HAVE NOTHING BETTER TO DO.
IT IS HARD ENOUGH FOR US TO PROVIDE THE APPROPRIATE ACCESS
TO ENOUGH SAN FRANCISCANS TO ACTUALLY GET THE JOB DONE
AND NOW TO BE FORCED TO OPEN THIS UP TO EVERY YAHOO AROUND
THE WORLD WHO WANTS TO OPINE WITH ABSOLUTELY NOTHING TO DO
WITH THEIR LIVES IS WRONG. THIS IS ENCOURAGING US TO
EXPLORE WAYS TO SHUT DOWN PUBLIC COMMENT.
THIS IS EXPLORING US TO LOOK FOR WORKAROUNDS AND LOOPHOLES.
THIS IS ENCOURAGING US TO BUY SOME KIND OF TECHNOLOGY SYSTEM
THAT CRASHES EVERY TEN MINUTES JUST SO WE CAN SHUT OUT THESE
WEIRD VOICES. AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT ACCESS
TO GOVERNMENT, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT PROMOTING VOICES LIKE THE
YOUTH COMMISSION, LIKE PEOPLE HAVE TRADITIONALLY BEEN
MARGINALIZED I CAN IMAGINE THAT THIS IS A QUOTE THOUGHTFUL WAY
TO DO THAT BUT IT IS THE OPPOSITE.
IT IS STUPID AND IT IS HYPOCRITICAL.
I AM SO RELUCTANT TO VOTE YES BUT I ALSO DON'T WANT US TO GET
SUED AND JUST COUGH MONEY DOWN THE DRAIN.
>> SO YEAH, WITH APPRECIATION FOR SUPERVISOR SHERYL'S USE OF
YAHOO AND WACKADOO ALL IN THE SAME COMMENTS, SUPERVISOR CHAN
HE ALSO SAYS STUPID. >> I'M LIKE WOW.
WELL I MEAN I THINK IF SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND SUPERVISOR SHERYL ARE IN AGREEMENT THIS MUST BE NOT
GOOD. >> THIS IS THAT SOUNDS
TERRIBLE. SO I THINK IF I MAY DO MY DUE
DILIGENCE IS THAT IF I MAY THROUGH PRESENT AMENDMENT IS TO
ASK THE DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY TO HELP ME UNDERSTAND BETTER
UNDERSTAND WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN THE EVENT THAT THIS THIS
BOARD VOTED AGAINST THIS LEGISLATION AND BECAUSE OF I
SHARE ALREADY INDICATED A LOT POTENTIAL LAWSUITS BUT HOW
WOULD THAT ACTUALLY WORKS? >> SURE.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSTY
THIS REQUIREMENT COMES FROM SENATE BILL 707 THAT WAS
APPROVED BY THE LEGISLATURE LAST YEAR WHICH IS AN AMENDMENT
TO THE BROWN ACT WHICH GOVERNS PUBLIC MEETINGS IN THE STATE
AND I THINK WHAT COULD HAPPEN IS A MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC WHO
TRIED TO CALL INTO A MEETING AS THEY ARE THERE HAS THE THEY
WILL HAVE THE RIGHT TO STARTING IN JULY 1ST AND DID NOT HAVE
THAT ABILITY TO DO SO. THEY COULD BRING A BRING A
CLAIM AGAINST THE CITY UNDER THE BROWN ACT AND WE COULD BE
FORCED TO YOU KNOW THE COURT COULD GRANT AN INJUNCTION.
THE PERSON COULD BE ENTITLED TO ATTORNEYS FEES.
>> SO THAT'S SORT OF A PATH I SEE.
SO ESSENTIALLY IT IS NOT THAT WE WILL BE SUED BY TWO STATE
LEGISLATURE OR TWO STATE GOVERNMENT BUT ESSENTIALLY IS
THEN IT CREATES A LIABILITY AND A POTENTIAL CAUSE FOR THE
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC BASED ON THE STATE BROWN ACT REQUIREMENT
AND SUE THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO IN VIOLATION OF
THE BROWN YES, THAT'S CORRECT. HMM.
THANK YOU TOBIAS MELGAR THANK YOU.
>> AS AT PRESENT AMENDMENTS NOS I'M ACTUALLY NOT AS YOU KNOW
AGAINST PEOPLE YOU KNOW CALLING BECAUSE I DO THINK IT PROVIDES
AN IMPORTANT VENUE FOR PEOPLE WHO CANNOT COME IN PERSON
PREGNANT WOMEN, PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES.
HOWEVER, AS YOU ALL VERY WELL KNOW WHAT MY PATIENCE FOR
NONSENSE IS VERY SHORT. I APPRECIATE THAT WE HAVE SOME
CLARIFICATION HERE ABOUT WHAT THE PRESIDING OFFICER CAN DO
DURING A MEETING TO, YOU KNOW, STOP THE ABUSE OF PUBLIC
COMMENT TO ABUSE A PUBLIC OFFICIAL OR TARGET SOMEBODY IN.
I AM WONDERING HOW MUCH FLEXIBILITY WE HAVE TO FURTHER
THAT. YOU KNOW, IN ADDITION TO WHAT
WE HAVE RIGHT NOW IN TERMS OF LIKE WHAT WE SAW AS SUPERVISOR
WALTON WAS ALLUDING DURING THE PANDEMIC WE SAW MEMBERS OF THIS
BODY BEING TARGETED BECAUSE OF THEIR RELIGION, BECAUSE OF
THEIR SEXUAL ORIENTATION, BECAUSE OF THEIR GENDER.
WE'VE SEEN IT ALL. AND SO I AM WONDERING YOU KNOW,
I THINK I LIKE THIS LANGUAGE AND IT'S CLEAR IN HOW MUCH
FLEXIBILITY DO WE HAVE, YOU KNOW, IN THE FUTURE TO SORT OF
PUT ORDER IN TO PROTECT THE MEMBERS OF THIS BODY OR OTHER
BODIES WHEN PEOPLE ARE BEING ABUSIVE?
>> THANKS FOR THE QUESTION. SO THE THE STATE LAW THAT WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT HERE PROVIDES DISCRETION TO BASICALLY IT
PROVIDES THAT MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC, INCLUDING THOSE WHO
CALL IN IF THEY DISRUPT THE MEETING, THERE IS A BASIS TO
REMOVE THEM FROM IT. SO WE WOULD NEED TO LOOK AT
THAT KIND OF ON A CASE BY CASE BASIS AND WHEN SOMEONE COMES
IN PERSON AND GIVES PUBLIC COMMENT OF THE TYPE THAT YOU'RE
DISCUSSING, THERE ARE WAYS THAT WE CAN WE CAN REDIRECT THEM.
WE CAN HAVE THE CLERK CAN READ A STATEMENT ABOUT
ANTI-HARASSMENT AND THAT THE BOARD DOESN'T ADOPT THOSE
COMMENTS. SO IT'S REALLY GOING TO DEPEND
ON A CASE BY CASE BASIS AND WE CAN LOOK AT AMENDING THE RULE
IN THE FUTURE IF IT BECOMES A PROBLEM AND WHERE THE LINE IS
THERE. BUT THERE ARE, YOU KNOW, FIRST
AMENDMENT ISSUES HERE. THERE ARE PUBLIC ACCESS UNDER
THE BROWN ACT ISSUES HERE. SO IT'S A IT'S A LITTLE BIT
TRICKY, UNDERSTANDABLE AND I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING THE
CONVERSATION AND NOT WITHSTANDING FIRST AMENDMENT
RIGHTS. YOU KNOW, I WHAT IS THE
DEFINITION OF DISRUPTION? YOU KNOW, AND IF THE SAME
INDIVIDUAL COMES TO EVERY MEETING AND SAYS SAY
ANTI-SEMITE THINGS OR YOU KNOW, MISOGYNIST THINGS LIKE HOW HOW
DO WE WHAT FLEXIBILITY DO WE HAVE UNDER THE BROWNBACK TO
LIMIT THEIR ACCESS? SO I HAVE ALL KINDS OF
QUESTIONS ABOUT WHAT WE CAN DO WITH OUR OWN RULES OF ORDER TO
COMPLY AND ALSO ALLOW US TO CONDUCT BUSINESS AND ALSO LIKE
PROTECT EACH OTHER. BUT YOU KNOW, I LOOK FORWARD TO
THE CONVERSATION. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL ON A DOUBLE CLICK ON WHAT SUPERVISOR MELGAR
SAID THERE I THINK THOSE ARE THE VOICES YOU KNOW THAT YOU
MENTIONED THE BEGINNING LIKE A PREGNANT WOMAN OR SOMEONE WITH
WITH PHYSICAL DISABILITY THAT WOULD PREVENT THEM BEING THOSE
ARE THE VOICES WE NEED TO PRIORITIZE.
WE NEED TO CREATE ROOM FOR AND CREATE ACCESS FOR AND I
THINK ALL YOUR QUESTIONS IN THE SUBSEQUENT ANSWERS THAT THAT
SADLY THERE'S NOT ENOUGH CLARITY AROUND WHICH I DON'T
MEAN AS A CRITICISM I ASSURE YOU THAT IS WHERE MY ANGER
AROUND THIS COMES FROM AND WHY I THINK THE PEOPLE WHO DO NEED
ACCESS TO THIS REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT I BELIEVE THAT THEY
WILL END UP GETTING CROWDED OUT AND GETTING EVEN MORE
FRUSTRATED THAN WE DO AND THAT IS A DISASTER.
>> SEBASTIAN, THANK YOU. I THINK THAT I WANT TO CREDIT
OUR CLERK AND HER TEAM FOR DOING A GOOD JOB FOR REMOTE
PUBLIC COMMONS ACCOMMODATING THOSE WITH DISABILITIES.
WE HAVE THAT DURING BUDGET SO I'M VERY GRATEFUL FOR TRYING TO
BUDGET PUBLIC COMMON DAY SO I'M REALLY GRATEFUL FOR THAT.
I DO HAVE A QUESTION ABOUT HOW WOULD WHETHER IT'S POSSIBLE
WITHIN THIS FRAMEWORK BACK FROM THE STATE LEGISLATURE OR BROWN
ACT AMENDMENT IS THAT WE COULD NARROW THE REMOTE PUBLIC
COMMONS TO AGAIN LIKE IS THERE A WAY TO NARROW IT TO TO
RESIDENTS AND PEOPLE THAT HAVE DISABILITIES AND REQUIRE
ACCOMMODATION AND THEN TO ALLOW PEOPLE WHO ARE OUT OF STATE TO
ALSO HAVE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMONS REMOTE PUBLIC COMMONS BUT BY
THROUGH WRITTEN RECORDS LIKE IS THERE SUCH THING THAT WE COULD
DO SO OR IS IT TOO MUCH A SUPERVISOR CHAN
AND UNFORTUNATELY THERE IS NOTHING IN THE STATE BILL THAT
WOULD ALLOW THE BOARD TO LIMIT THE WHERE THE PEOPLE ARE
CALLING FROM OR TO YOU KNOW WEED OUT PEOPLE WHO ARE NOT
ACTUALLY IN SAN FRANCISCO OR CALIFORNIA BUT WHAT IS THERE A
CLIFF SORRY I JUST WANT TO JUST ONE FOLLOW UP LIKE REMOTE POP
OF COMMONS. IS IT DEFINE REMOTE PUBLIC
COMMONS AS THROUGH VOICE OVER OR A REMOTE COMMONS?
I MEAN A WRITTEN PUBLIC COMMONS IS ALSO REMOTE POP OF COMMONS.
>> NOW THE BILL REQUIRES EITHER A IT REQUIRES AN ELECTRONIC
FORM OF EITHER CALLING IN OR HAVING LIKE A ZOOM TYPE
MEETING. IT COULD BE THE BOARD COULD DO
EITHER YOU COULD HAVE A CALL IN LINE OR IT COULD HAVE A ZOOM
FUNCTION. SO I THINK THE CLERK HAS
ALREADY A PLAN FOR HOW THIS IS GOING TO WORK.
>> THANK YOU. >> RESOLUTION THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AND I JUST WANT TO JUST STATE TO COLLEAGUES THAT
DURING COMMITTEE WE TRY TO ASK QUESTIONS ABOUT ALTERNATIVES
EVERY ISSUE AND CONCERN YOU BRING UP TRUST ME WE'VE WE'VE
TALKED ABOUT IT BECAUSE I DON'T COMPLETELY AGREE THAT WE THAT
IT SAYS WE CAN'T SET OUR RULES IN OUR OUR OWN POLICIES ON HOW
WE DEAL WITH PUBLIC COMMENT BECAUSE WE ALREADY DO IT FOR
INDIVIDUALS WITH DISABILITIES. WE ALREADY MAKE ACCOMMODATIONS
FOR FOLKS WHO REACH OUT. AND SO I DON'T SEE WHY WE
COULDN'T DO THE SAME THING. IT'S NOT INTERPRETED THAT WE
COULD BY ADVICE OF COUNSEL BUT WE DEFINITELY BROUGHT UP
SEVERAL DIFFERENT WAYS TO TRY TO ADDRESS THIS AND I KNOW THE
CLERK THANK YOU SO MUCH TO YOUR TEAM ALSO HAS REALLY LOOKED
INTO THIS TO SEE WHAT POSSIBILITIES EXIST.
AND SO I THINK THAT WE WILL OF COURSE CONTINUE TO WORK TO SEE
WHAT WE CAN DO TO MAKE SURE THAT THIS IS ACTUALLY
BENEFICIAL TO OUR CONSTITUENTS. >> BUT WE ARE PRETTY MUCH
FORCED TO VOTE FOR THIS. >> I MEAN I REALLY DID NOT WANT
TO SUPPORT IT AND REALLY WANTED TO VOTE AGAINST IT IN COMMITTEE
BUT THIS IS ONE OF THOSE THINGS WHERE IT WILL COST US A LOT OF
MONEY TO GO AGAINST THIS AND I DON'T THINK THIS IS THE TIME
THROUGH THE PRESIDENT TO THE MEMBERS IF I COULD ADDRESS THIS
ISSUE PLEASE. THANK YOU.
SO THE CITY ATTORNEY HAS INTERPRETED THAT THIS REMOTE
PUBLIC COMMENT WOULD OCCUR DURING BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
MEETINGS, NOT YOUR COMMITTEE MEETINGS.
AND SO WE ARE LOOKING INTO LEGISLATIVE SYSTEMS WHICH COULD
REALLY HANDLE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT BUT SPECIFICALLY TO
ENCOURAGE INDIVIDUALS TO SIGN UP IN ADVANCE THE WAY WE'RE
GOING TO HANDLE THE PUBLIC COMMENT IS WE'LL TAKE THOSE WHO
ARE HERE IN PERSON FIRST AS PEOPLE SIGN UP FROM MONDAY OR
TUESDAY TO THE BOARD MEETING WILL THEN BRING IN THE REMOTE
CALLERS IN THE ORDER THAT THEY SIGNED UP.
WE WILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO MOVE ADA UP IF THAT IS THEIR
REQUEST WE ARE WORKING HARD TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE'RE GOING TO
HANDLE LANGUAGE ACCESS WITH THE REMOTE PUBLIC SYSTEM ULTIMATELY
WE ARE NOT REQUIRING PEOPLE TO GIVE THEIR NAMES BUT IF YOU'RE
CALLING IN ON A REGULAR BASIS WE KNOW INDIVIDUALS TYPICALLY
WORK WITH OUR OFFICE WHO ARE SERIOUS COMMENTERS BUT YOU DO
NOT HAVE TO GIVE YOUR NAME AND THOSE INDIVIDUALS IF THEY
SIGN IT, IF THEY JUST COME TO THE MEETING WHILE IT'S
OCCURRING WE WILL PIPE YOU IN. WE WORKED WITH THE DEPUTY CITY
ATTORNEY BRETT ROSSI TO MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE PROVIDING
MULTIPLE INFORMATIONAL REDIRECTIONS THAT IF YOU ARE
NOT SPEAKING WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION WE
WILL ASK YOU ONE TIME DURING YOUR SPEECH OTHERWISE WE WILL
MOVE ON TO THE NEXT CALLER. SO THAT IS ESSENTIALLY HOW WE
INTEND ON HANDLING THIS. I WILL AS I CONTINUE TO DO WORK
WITH OUR OUR GENERAL COUNSEL BRAD ROSSI ON WHAT IS
APPROPRIATE TO REMOVE SOMEONE FROM PUBLIC COMMENT IF THEY'RE
SPEAKING ABOUT SOMEONE'S BEARD OR USING FOUL ALL LANGUAGE
ABOUT AN INDIVIDUAL'S IN A PROTECTED CLASS.
>> OTHERWISE MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC ARE FREE TO CRITIQUE
YOUR POLICIES, YOUR VOTES, YOUR LEGISLATIVE ITEMS, YOUR CLERK
PERHAPS IF THEY'RE CRITIQUING YOU TO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE
THAT IS ALSO BEEN ALLOWED TYPICALLY BUT IF THEY GET
PERSONAL WITH YOU AND WE CANNOT REDIRECT THEM TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE THAT HAS ALSO BEEN A REQUIREMENT THAT I MOVE ON TO
THE NEXT CALLER OR NEXT PERSON IN LINE BUT I WILL AGAIN BE
VERY CAREFUL IF I AM DOING A PUBLIC COMMENT DURING YOUR
BOARD MEETING NOT TO MINIMIZE ANYONE'S RIGHTS FOR WHAT THEY
ARE ENTITLED TO OTHERWISE SAY TO YOU AND MR. PRESIDENT, THIS
BEGINS NEXT TUESDAY SO WE WILL BE PUTTING NOTICES ON OUR
WEBSITE HAVING IT AT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AND MAKING SURE
THAT THOSE WHO ARE ANSWERING THE PHONES IN OUR OFFICE
AND PROVIDING INFORMATION TO EACH OF YOUR OFFICES, THE
TELEPHONE NUMBER TO CALL IN IF INDIVIDUALS WANT TO SIGN UP
IN ADVANCE. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK
WITHOUT ROBUST DISCUSSION UNLESS ANYONE NEEDS A ROLL CALL
I WILL SAY THAT WE WILL TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> YOU ARE FIRST TO INTRODUCE
NEW BUSINESS. ALL RIGHT.
I HAVE A RESOLUTION, AN ORDINANCE AND AN IN MEMORIAM
FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION OF SUPPORT FOR
ASSEMBLY BILL 1573 THE UNSEEN AND UNHEARD HOUSING ACT
AUTHORED BY ASSEMBLYMEMBER BRIAN AND COAUTHORED BY
ASSEMBLYMEMBER STEPHANIE WHICH WOULD ADD ADD SURVIVORS OF
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE, SEXUAL ASSAULT AND HUMAN TRAFFICKING
TO THE DEFINITION OF TARGET POPULATION UNDER CALIFORNIA'S
PLANNING AND ZONING LAW. CURRENT LAW REQUIRES CITIES
AND COUNTIES TO IDENTIFY AND PLAN FOR THE SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING NEEDS OF SPECIFIED TARGET POPULATIONS IN THEIR
GENERAL PLANS AS PART OF THE HOUSING ELEMENT, JURISDICTIONS
ARE REQUIRED TO DETERMINE THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE IN EACH TARGET
POPULATION AND FACTOR THEIR HOUSING NEEDS INTO THE OVERALL
HOUSING ELEMENT ALONG WITH AN ANALYSIS OF ALL THE PROGRAMS
AVAILABLE FOR SUCH POPULATION. THE CURRENT LIST INCLUDES
VETERANS THE ELDERLY, PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES, INDIVIDUALS
AND INDIVIDUALS EXITING INSTITUTIONAL SETTINGS
AND OTHERS SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE, SEXUAL
ASSAULT AND HUMAN TRAFFICKING ARE NOT CURRENTLY ON THAT LIST.
AB 1573 WOULD FIX THAT. >> THIS MATTERS BECAUSE
SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE ,SEXUAL ASSAULT AND HUMAN
TRAFFICKING HAVE UNIQUE NEEDS THAT ARE NOT CURRENTLY BEING
MET AMONG THE BROADER HOMELESS POPULATION SURVIVORS ARE
DISPROPORTIONATELY REPRESENTED REMAIN ON HOUSE FOR LONGER
PERIODS, RETURN TO HOMELESSNESS MORE FREQUENTLY AND ARE LESS
LIKELY TO OBTAIN PERMANENT HOUSING BY INCLUDING SURVIVORS
AS A TARGET POPULATION AND CITY AND COUNTY'S HOUSING ELEMENTS.
THIS BILL WOULD ENCOURAGE GREATER UNDERSTANDING
AND ATTENTION TO THEIR SPECIFIC HOUSING NEEDS AND MEANINGFUL
STEP FORWARD AS WE WORK TO SUPPORT A PARTICULARLY
VULNERABLE POPULATION. I WANT TO THANK THE WOMEN'S
HOUSING COALITION AND ESPECIALLY ROMA GUY FOR
BRINGING THE ISSUE AND THIS LEGISLATION TO MY ATTENTION
AND I THANK RONALD FOR JOY IN MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK ON
THE RESOLUTION. SECONDLY, I'M INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION TO RAISE THE CITY ATTORNEY'S DELEGATED SETTLEMENT
AUTHORITY FROM $25,000 TO $100,000, MODERNIZE OUR CLAIMS
PROCESS AND REORGANIZE PROVISIONS REGARDING
SETTLEMENTS. THE CURRENT $25,000 THRESHOLD
HAS NOT BEEN ADJUSTED IN 40 YEARS NOT EVEN FOR INFLATION A
$25,000 SETTLEMENT TODAY IS A RELATIVELY SMALL SUM YET IT
STILL TRIGGERS THE SAME FULL BOARD APPROVAL PROCESS AS FAR
LARGER AND MORE CONSEQUENTIAL MATTERS MATTERS CURRENTLY
PLAINTIFFS HAVE REACHED AGREEMENT WITH THE CITY ARE
WAITING SOMETIMES FOR MONTHS WHILE ROUTINE SMALL VALUE
SETTLEMENTS WORK THEIR WAY THROUGH THE APPROVAL QUEUE.
JUDGES HAVE BEEN CRITICAL OF HOW LONG THIS PROCESS TAKES.
IT MAKES SENSE TO CUT DOWN THE TIME IT TAKES TO PROCESS
SMALLER VALUE SETTLEMENTS BY INCREASING INCREASING THE
DELEGATED SETTLEMENT THRESHOLD .
>> IN PRACTICE MOST SETTLEMENTS UNDER 100,000 DOLLARS ARE
APPROVED WITHOUT SUBSTANTIVE DEBATE FROM 2020 TO 20 2,540%
OF SETTLEMENTS THAT CAME TO THE BOARD FOR APPROVAL FELL BETWEEN
25,000 AND $100,000. THIS CHANGE WOULD REMOVE THOSE
ROUTINE ITEMS FROM THE BOARD FREEING UP THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
TIME CITY STAFF TIME IN THE BOARD'S OWN TIME FOR MORE
CONSEQUENTIAL WORK. THIS LEGISLATION STILL PROTECTS
OVERSIGHT. THE ORDINANCE INCLUDES AN
ANNUAL REPORTING REQUIREMENTS THAT GIVES THE BOARD AND THE
PUBLIC FULL VISIBILITY INTO SETTLEMENTS BETWEEN 25,000
AND $100,000 DISCLOSING THE SETTLEMENT THE AMOUNT THE
DEPARTMENT INVOLVED AND THE GENERAL SUBJECT MATTER OF THE
CLAIM TRANSPARENCY IS PRESERVED WHILE ELIMINATING UNNECESSARY
DELAY. THE LEGISLATION ALSO TAKES THE
OPPORTUNITY TO MODERNIZE OUR CLAIMS PROCESS, REMOVE
PROVISIONS THAT HAVE BECOME OBSOLETE AND REORGANIZE THE
SETTLEMENT FRAMEWORK SO IT'S CLEANER AND EASIER TO
ADMINISTER GOING FORWARD. I WANT TO THANK BRAD RUSSI FROM
THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND HIS TEAM FOR BRINGING US
THE LEGISLATION. I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY NAMED
SCULLY IN MY OFFICE FOR HER WORK ON IT.
AND FINALLY I WOULD LIKE TO THANK MY CO SPONSOR SUPERVISOR
ALAN WONG. FINALLY COLLEAGUES, I'M ASKING
THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF GLORY DIAO
DELARIA, FORMER OWNER OF TILBURY SALON IN GLEN PARK
AND BELOVED SISTER WIFE, GRANDMOTHER AND MOTHER TO MARY
AND LARRY GLORY DIED ON JUNE 21ST, 2026 AT THE AGE OF 92
WITH HER FAMILY BY HER SIDE. >> SHE WAS BORN IN THE
PHILIPPINES ON NOVEMBER 15TH, 1933.
IN 1956 SHE CROSSED THE OCEAN AND MOVED TO CALIFORNIA
DREAMING OF BUILDING A NEW LIFE AND A HOME.
THAT SAME YEAR SHE MARRIED SANTIAGO DE LARRY AND THE TWO
SETTLED IN AND MOVED TO AN APARTMENT IN THE HAIGHT-ASHBURY
WHERE THEY HAD THEIR FIRST SON. A FEW YEARS LATER LOOKING FOR A
LARGER HOME, THE FAMILY DISCOVERED GLEN PARK AND FELL
IN LOVE WITH SHOPS, GARDENS AND TIGHT KNIT COMMUNITY.
>> THEY DECIDED TO MOVE THERE. GLORIA EARNED HER COSMETOLOGY
LICENSE AT MARINELLO SCHOOL OF BEAUTY IN 1960 AND BEGAN THE
CAREER THAT WOULD BECOME HER CALLING.
>> AFTER THE MOVE TO GLEN PARK, SHE RENTED A SMALL STOREFRONT
ON DIAMOND STREET AND OPENED THE DOORS TO DELIRIOUS BEAUTY
SALON ON NOVEMBER 6TH, 1968. OVER THE YEARS TWO LARRY'S
BEAUTY SALON GROUP GREW FROM A SALON INTO A NEIGHBORHOOD
GATHERING SPACE. CLIENTS CAME NOT ONLY FOR HER
TALENT AS A STYLIST, AS A HAIRSTYLIST BUT FOR COMFORT,
CONVERSATION AND THE WARMTH OF HER PRESENCE.
GLORIA WOULD MAKE HOUSE CALLS TO CLIENTS WHO WERE ILL OR
HOMEBOUND ENSURING THEY COULD STILL RECEIVE BEAUTY SERVICES
IN THE COMFORT OF THEIR HOMES. THROUGH HER VOLUNTEER WORK WITH
LOOK GOOD FEEL BETTER, SHE STYLED WIGS FOR WOMEN
UNDERGOING CANCER TREATMENT. ONE DAY GLORIA'S FAMILY NOTICED
A FOR SALE SIGN IN THE BUILDING ON HENRY STREET.
THE OWNER SPOKE WITH GLORIA AND AGREED TO SELL THE PROPERTY
TO HER ON ONE CONDITION THAT SHE VISIT HIS HOME WEEKLY TO
SHAMPOO AND SELL THE HAIR OF HIS ELDERLY HOMEBOUND WIFE.
GLORIA AGREED WITHOUT HESITATION AND IN 1975 TO
LARRY'S BEAUTIFUL BEAUTY SALON MOVED INTO THEIR PERMANENT
CURRENT HOME AT 660 HENRY STREET.
IN 1981 SHE ENROLLED HER DAUGHTER MARIANNE IN THE SAME
BEAUTY SCHOOL SHE HAD ATTENDED DECADES EARLIER.
GLORY WOULD EVENTUALLY PASS DOWN THE BUSINESS TO MARIAN.
GLORIA TOOK CARE OF PEOPLE HER CLIENTS, HER FAMILY AND HER
COMMUNITY. IN 2012, WHEN THE CHEERS
BOUTIQUE FACED EVICTION, SHE OFFERED THEM SUPPORT AND SPACE.
SHE TOOK CARE OF HER AGING HUSBAND UNTIL HIS DEATH IN 2006
AND OPENED HER HOME TO TWO OLDER SISTERS WHEN THEY NEEDED
CARE. HER LEGACY OF SERVICE,
COMPASSION AND GENEROSITY LIVES ON THROUGH HER FAMILY AND IN
ALL THE LIVES SHE TOUCHED. I WANT TO EXTEND MY AND OUR
BOARD'S DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO GLORIA'S FAMILY ESPECIALLY HER
EXTRAORDINARY DAUGHTER AND LONGTIME CAREGIVER MARIAN.
REST IN PEACE, GLORIA. >> LARRY.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MILLER, THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, TODAY I WANT TO
ANNOUNCE A DRAFTING REQUEST THAT I MADE TO OUR CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO AMEND OUR RENT ORDINANCE TO RESPOND TO A
TROUBLE PATTERN THAT WE HAVE BEEN SEEING ONCE AGAIN IN SAN
FRANCISCO RECENTLY. WE HAVE SEEN A GROWING NUMBER
OF NEWS STORIES ABOUT TENANTS FACING OUTRAGEOUS RENT
INCREASES OR DUBIOUS CLAIMS OF VIOLATING THEIR LEASES WHEN THE
REAL MOTIVATION SEEMS TO BE TO PUSH AT LONG TERM RENT CONTROL
TENANTS OUT. IT'S EVEN HAPPENING TO TENANTS
WHO ARE FAIRLY WELL OFF. SO WHEN THE TENANTS UNION
APPROACHED ME WITH EXAMPLES FROM THEIR COUNSELING CLINIC I
AGREED IT IS TIME THAT WE DO SOMETHING LEGISLATIVELY.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN THROUGH TECH BOOMS AND SEEN INTENSE
SPECULATION AT WORK BEFORE BACK IN THE 1990S AND I'M GIVING
AWAY MY OLD AGE. I WORKED AT SAINT PETER'S
HOUSING COMMITTEE WHICH LATER BECAME CASA HOSTED JUST CAUSE
IT WAS AT THE FOREFRONT OF THE GENTRIFICATION FIGHTS DURING
THE FIRST.COM BOOM. WE SAW FAR TOO MANY LONGTIME
TENANTS IN IMMIGRANT FAMILIES FACE DISPLACED MEN NOT BECAUSE
THEY COULDN'T PAY THEIR RENT BUT BECAUSE LANDLORDS WANTED
DIFFERENT HIGHER INCOME OCCUPANTS.
AS THE ECONOMY ACCELERATES WE'RE SEEING THAT PRESSURE
RETURN WITH RISING RENTS AND HOMES SELLING FOR A MILLION
OVER ASKING PRICE IN TIMES OF HIGH REWARD, SPECULATORS WILL
PUSH THE ENVELOPE OF WHAT IS LEGAL.
THE TENANTS UNION FOLKS TELL ME THAT MANY OF THESE EVICTION
ATTEMPTS ARE LIKELY UNLAWFUL BUT IT IS STILL IT STILL
REQUIRES TENANTS TO FIND THE LAWYERS AND TIME TAKE ON THE
ANXIETY IN ORDER TO STAY IN THEIR HOMES AND MANY WILL
JUST GIVE UP. IT IS NOT ENOUGH TO BUILD MORE
HOUSING AND HOPE THAT PRICES WILL COME DOWN.
WE HAVE TO DO THAT. WE ALSO HAVE TO PROTECT
FAMILIES HERE NOW FROM THE WAVES OF SPECULATION
IN UNSCRUPULOUS LANDLORDS. SO I AM WORKING WITH
KNOWLEDGEABLE TENANT ATTORNEYS TO TIGHTEN THE DEFINITION OF
EVICT ABLE OFFENSES INCLUDING THE NOW VAGUE DEFINITIONS OF
NUISANCE HOARDING AND TO STRENGTHEN WHAT CONSTITUTES
HARASSMENT UNDER THE RENT ORDINANCE.
>> THERE ARE FEW DETERRENTS FOR LAWYERS WHO ASSISTANT TRUMPED
UP BREACH OF CLAIMS OF CONTRACT CLAIMS SINCE THEY WILL GET PAID
REGARDLESS IF THEY FAIL. SO WE CAN ALSO HELP CURB THAT
PRACTICE. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
SHYANNE CHEN FOLLOWING HER GREAT WORK ON THE TENANT
PROTECTION ORDINANCE FOR HER EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AND THE
REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WANG. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO DESIGNATE AND COMMEMORATE
NORIEGA STREET BETWEEN 19TH AND 33RD AVENUE AS A SUNSET
HEALTH CARE CORRIDOR. FOR DECADES THE SUNSET HAS HAD
LIMITED ACCESS TO HOSPITALS, URGENT CARE AND MAJOR HEALTH
CARE SYSTEMS MEANING MANY RESIDENTS HAVE HAD TO TRAVEL
OUTSIDE THE NEIGHBORHOOD FOR CARE.
BUT ALONG THIS STRETCH IN NORIEGA, COMMUNITY PROVIDERS
STEPPED UP CHINESE HOSPITALS SUNSET HEALTH SERVICES, NEMS
ALL AMERICAN MEDICAL GROUP, LOCAL MEDICAL GROUPS, DENTISTS,
OPTOMETRISTS PHARMACIES AND WELLNESS PROVIDERS HAVE
BUILT A CORRIDOR OF AFFORDABLE, CULTURALLY COMPETENT
AND LINGUISTICALLY ACCESSIBLE CARE CLOSE TO HOME.
THIS DESIGNATION AND COMMEMORATION HONORS
AND AND SUPPORTS THE CLINICIANS STAFF AND COMMUNITY
INSTITUTIONS THAT HAVE SERVED THE SUNSET FAMILIES FOR DECADES
AND AFFIRMS OUR COMMITMENT TO EXPANDING HEALTH CARE ACCESS ON
THE WEST SIDE. WE'LL ALSO ENCOURAGE MORE
TRAFFIC AND SUPPORT LOCAL BUSINESSES.
I WANT TO THANK THE HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS
INCLUDING NEMS, AMG AND CHINESE HOSPITAL WHO HAS HELPED SUPPORT
AND BRING THIS IDEA FORWARD AND LOOK FORWARD TO YOUR
SUPPORT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WANG.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
IN SUPPORT OF THE LICENSE RENEWAL FOR KGO-TV ALSO LOCALLY
KNOWN AS ABC CHANNEL SEVEN. >> IN THIS WRESTLE WITH THIS
RESOLUTION WE'RE URGING THE FEDERAL COMMUNICATIONS
COMMISSION TO QUICKLY REVIEW AND APPROVE THE STATION'S
APPLICATION BASED ON THE STATION'S DECADES LONG TRACK
RECORDS OF SERVICE DEVOTION TO THE LOCAL COMMUNITY
AND COMPLIANCE SINCE 1949 KGO-TV HAS BEEN RELIABLY
SERVING THE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO, OAKLAND, SAN JOSE
AND THE BAY AREA COMMUNITY FOR OVER 75 YEARS.
THE STATION PROVIDES INVALUABLE NEWS COVERAGE, INVESTIGATIVE
REPORTING AND COMMUNITY CENTRIC PROGRAMING AS WELL AS PUBLIC
SAFETY COORDINATION DURING THE EMERGENCY THAT KEEPS MILLIONS
OF RESIDENTS INFORMED, PREPARED AND CONNECTED.
LAST MONTH KGO TV FILMED A BROADCAST LICENSE RENEWAL
APPLICATION SORRY. LAST MONTH KGO TV FILED A
BROADCAST LICENSE RENEWAL APPLICATION WITH THE FEDERAL
COMMUNICATIONS COMMISSION AFTER THEY ABRUPTLY ACCELERATED THE
APPLICATION TIMELINE FOR KGO TV AND SEVEN OTHER ABC OWNED
STATIONS. AND THIS ACCELERATION IS WELL
AHEAD. IT'S ORIGINALLY SCHEDULE 2028
DEADLINE. BROADCAST JOURNALISM
PARTICULARLY THOSE THAT IT'S INDEPENDENT IS PROTECTED BY OUR
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS TO FREE SPEECH AND FREEDOM OF THE PRESS
AND SHALL REMAIN AND CONTINUE TO REMAIN INDEPENDENT FROM ANY
POLITICAL INTERFERENCE. THE FCC NEEDS TO EVALUATE THE
RENEWAL APPLICATION BASED ON THE STATION'S MERITS
AND LONGSTANDING COMPLIANCE A FAILURE TO RENEW KGO TV'S
LICENSE WILL CREATE A SIGNIFICANT GAP WITHIN THE BAY
AREA MEDIA LANDSCAPE MEDIA LANDSCAPE.
ELIMINATING A TRUSTED SOURCE OF LOCAL NEWS CULTURE INFORMATION
AND EMERGENCY COORDINATION THAT RESIDENTS AND ALL OF US
INCLUDING THE POLICYMAKER AND CITY GOVERNMENT RELY ON.
I WOULD LIKE TO COMMEND KGO TV'S DEDICATED TEAM OF
JOURNALISTS, PRODUCTION CREWS AND STAFF WHO HAVE BEEN SERVING
THE PUBLIC'S INTEREST EVERY DAY.
I URGE SAN FRANCISCANS TO PARTICIPATE IN THE PUBLIC
COMMENT PROCESS BY SUBMITTING THEIR SUPPORT ONLINE AT PUBLIC
FILES. FCC.GOV.
BEFORE THE JULY 29 DEADLINE AND IN ADDITION COLLEAGUES, I
WOULD LIKE TO ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN HONOR OF MR. STAN
LOS CHAN WHO PASSED AWAY ON JUNE 10TH, 2026 AT THE AGE OF
86. THROUGH PERSONAL EXAMPLE STAN
LEE STAN LAWS, STAN LEE CHAN INSPIRE AND INSTILL IN HIS
CHILDREN SO MUCH SO MUCH KINDNESS, SELFLESSNESS
AND POSITIVITY. THERE ARE COUNTLESS TIMES
IN WHICH MR. CHAN WOULD DRIVE FRIENDS AND RELATIVES HOME
AFTER A VISIT TO HIS FRIENDS AND FAMILIES AND IT'S A
TESTAMENT TO HIS GENEROSITY AND COMPASSION.
OFTEN THE RIDES WOULD BE AN HOUR EACH WAY BUT IT WAS NEVER
IN DOUBT THAT IT WAS THE RIGHT THING TO DO.
MR. CHAN ALSO DEMONSTRATED A TREMENDOUS SENSE OF HUMOR
AND USES CHARM AND WIT TO MAKE A LASTING IMPRESSION ON
EVERYONE HE MET AS A WAITER IN CHINESE RESTAURANTS FOR MOST
OF HIS LIFE. MR. CHAN STAND AS CHANCE FOR
TRANSFORM HIS CHARISMA INTO A STRENGTH AND SUPERPOWER TO
PROVIDE FOR HIS FAMILY. HIS SON DOMINICK GOT TO WORK
ALONGSIDE HIM AS A WAITER DURING HIS SUMMERS IN COLLEGE
AND GOT TO SEE FIRST HAND HOW CHARMING AND HARDWORKING MR.
CHAN WAS. AND AS MR. STANLEY CHAN GOT
OLDER HE TRANSITION TO A JOB WITH A WITH THE BROOKLYN PUBLIC
LIBRARY IN SUNSET PARK AND ABSOLUTELY LOVED THAT JOB.
AS HE COULD SHOW HIS HUMOR AND CHARM TO THE PUBLIC WITHOUT
WORRYING ABOUT TIPS AS WAGES. IT WAS A GOOD PAYING UNION JOB
. AS A MEMBER OF THE AMERICAN
FEDERATION OF STATE, COUNTY AND MUNICIPAL EMPLOYEES
DISTRICT COUNCIL 37 AND HE WAS ABLE TO SECURE A MODEST PENSION
BECAUSE OF IT. AFTER HE RETIRED AS 78 YEARS
OLD, HE LEARNED WITHIN A YEAR THAT HE HAD PARKINSON'S
DISEASE. MR. CHAN'S FAMILY IT'S BEEN
THEIR HOME TO LOVINGLY PROVIDE THAT TO PROVIDE CARE FOR HIM
AND HIS WIFE WHO PASSED AWAY IN 2021.
IN LATTER YEARS THE PARKINSON'S ESCALATED BUT HE ALWAYS KEPT
HIS SENSE OF HUMOR. THE CARE TEAM AT UNLOCK WHERE
HE GOT HIS HEALTH CARE ALWAYS REMARK HOW FUNNY HE WAS DESPITE
THE CHALLENGES OF HIS DISEASE. HE SPENT HIS LAST DAYS IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND HAD A PROFOUND IMPACT ON HIS FAMILY AND IS
SURVIVED BY HIS CHILDREN ANDY, BETTY AND DOMINIC AND HIS WIFE
SARA AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES, I WAS VERY
CONCERNED THIS WEEKEND SEEING REPORTS AND VIDEO FOOTAGE OF
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE CLASHING WITH SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS
AND VISITORS PARTICIPATING IN PRODUCTIVITY'S IN TWO
SEPARATE INCIDENTS ONE TRANS MARCH AND TWO AN EVENT KNOWN
AND SUDDENLY THE IMAGES OF POLICE IN FULL TACTICAL GEAR
HARKENED BACK TO THE COMPTON CAFETERIA RIOT OF 1966 IN WHICH
TRANS WOMEN AND DRAG QUEENS WERE PROTESTING POLICE
BRUTALITY. >> I HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT THE
DECISION MAKING TO DEPLOY OFFICERS IN FULL TACTICAL GEAR.
ANY OTHER DE-ESCALATION STRATEGIES USED BEFORE
DEPLOYING OFFICERS IN TACTICAL GEAR?
AND I'M ASKING IN THIS LETTER THAT THE COMPTROLLER ESTIMATE
THE RESPONSE OF US OF PD IN REGULAR AND OVERTIME HOURS
INTO BOTH OF THESE INCIDENTS. I'M SUBMITTING A LETTER OF
INQUIRY TO GAIN MORE CLARITY INTO THE POLICY CONTEXT
AND TIMELINE OF THESE EVENTS AND I'M REQUESTING THAT THE
DEPARTMENT AND COMPTROLLER SUBMIT THEIR RESPONSES BY
TUESDAY JULY 14TH. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD SUBMIT. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION
OF NEW BUSINESS. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
IF YOU'LL ALL LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER
ALONG THE CURTAINS. YOU MAY SPEAK TO ITEMS 15
THROUGH 19. THE ITEMS ON THE ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE PART OF THE AGENDA AND OTHER
GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION OF THE BOARD.
ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT HAS BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD
BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT
REQUIREMENT HAS OCCURRED. THE PODIUM THAT YOU'RE STANDING
IN FRONT OF MR. RIGHT I KNOW YOU KNOW BUT OTHERS MAY NOT.
IT HAS A TIMER ON IT. PLEASE MONITOR THE TIMER.
YOU'LL HEAR A SOFT BELL. THAT MEANS YOU HAVE 30S LEFT TO
WRAP UP YOUR COMMENTS BEFORE THE TWO MINUTE BELL.
>> THANK YOU. MR. WRIGHT, WELCOME.
>> I WANT TO OBJECT TO FUNDS BEING HIJACKED
AND MISAPPROPRIATED STOLE LAND OUT OF PROPOSITION C SAN
FRANCISCO VOTERS VOTED FOR PROPOSITION C TO HELP THE MOST
VULNERABLE PEOPLE IN VERY LOW AND LOW INCOME BRACKETS PEOPLE
WITH A COMBINATION OF BOTH MENTAL AND PHYSICAL
DISABILITIES TO SECURE THEIR HOUSING AND NOT LIVE ON THE
STREETS IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRAN CISCO.
AND I DON'T APPRECIATE THIS BOARD AND THE MAYOR TAKING
THOSE FUNDS AND HAVING MILLIONS OF DOLLARS BEING USED BY PEOPLE
IN HIGH INCOME BRACKETS UP TO 125 $30,000 A YEAR AND USE
THOSE FUNDS TO PAY FOR BABY SITTERS.
THOSE HIGH INCOME BRACKET PEOPLE TO PAY BABYSITTERS WHILE
THEY'RE WORKING AND TAKE CARE OF THEIR KIDS BABY SAID TO KIDS
WHEN THAT MONEY IS SUPPOSED TO BE SPENT FOR THE PEOPLE THAT'S
HOMELESS THAT NEED HOUSING AND SERVICES THAT'S THE MISSING
APPROPRIATIONS OF FUNDS AND A VIOLATION OF THE AMERICAN
DISABILITIES ACT BECAUSE THE PEOPLE WHO NEED HELP ARE
DISABLED. COMBINATION OF BOTH MENTAL
AND PHYSICAL DISABILITY THESE AND THESE SERVICES AND PEOPLE
IN WHEELCHAIRS. I OBJECTED TO THAT AND YOU'RE
JUST THE OPPOSITE OF ROBIN HOOD .
YOU DO THIS ADMINISTRATION, ADMINISTRATION, ADMINISTRATION.
YOU JUST OPPOSITE OF ROBIN HOOD.
ROBIN HOOD STEALS FROM THE RICH AND GIVES TO THE POOR.
YOU STEAL IT FROM PROGRAMS THAT'S VOTED FOR BY SAN
FRANCISCO VOTERS FOR THE POOR AND HAVE IT ENJOYED BY THE RICH
AS DISGUSTING AS THE DISGUSTING EXAMPLE THAT YOU'RE PUTTING
DOWN. >> AND ABOUT THIS TWO HUNDRED
AND $50 MILLION THAT YOU'RE TAKING AWAY FROM THE
HOSPITALITY HOUSE YOU NOT ONLY MAKING PEOPLE LOSE THEIR JOBS
BUT YOU DENYING SERVICES TO THE PEOPLE WHO THEY WORK AND SERVE
IN THE LOW INCOME BRACKET INCOME.
>> THANK YOU, MR. WRIGHT. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS LUCAS ELLA.
I'M WITH THE COALITION ON HOMELESSNESS.
TODAY I WANT TO SPEAK TO THE TWO YEAR ANNIVERSARY OF THE
LANDMARK US SUPREME COURT DECISION GRANTS PASS VERSUS
JOHNSON. THE QUESTION BEFORE THE COURT
IN GRANTS PASS WAS WHETHER A MUNICIPAL MUNICIPALITY'S
PRACTICE OF JAILING A PERSON WHO ERECTED A STRUCTURE IN THE
PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY EVEN WHEN THE MUNICIPALITY HAD NO SHELTER
TO OFFER THEM AMOUNTED TO CRUEL AND UNUSUAL PUNISHMENT.
THE COURT FOUND IN A63 DECISION THAT THIS CRIMINALIZATION BAN
WAS NOT CRUEL AND UNUSUAL AND AFTER THAT RULING WAS
ANNOUNCED, SAN FRANCISCO ELECTEDS MANY OF WHOM MAKE UP
THIS BOARD TODAY CELEBRATED THAT RULING AS COMMON SENSE
AND AS A CRUCIAL STEP IN OFFERING FLEXIBILITY TO SAN
FRANCISCO IN ADDRESSING ENCAMPMENTS.
>> AND OH HOW IT DID. MAYOR LEARY HAS TOUTED AN 85%
REDUCTION IN TENTS ALL WHILE OMITTING THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE
HE SUCCESSFULLY SHELTERED OR HOUSED IN THAT EFFORT TO THROW
PEOPLE IN JAIL FOR ERECTING SAID TENTS.
HE OF COURSE HAS NO IDEA HOW MANY.
THAT IS NOT THE METRIC THAT MATTERS.
I WANT TO HIGHLIGHT THOUGH AN OFTEN OVERLOOKED ASPECT OF THE
GRANTS PASS DECISION. >> THE THREE DEMOCRATIC
APPOINTED JUSTICES DISSENTED AND LEADING THE CHARGE WAS THE
LIBERAL LION SONIA SOTOMAYOR WHO READ HER DISSENT FROM THE
BENCH TO SHOW THE PROFOUND DISAGREEMENT SHE OPENS WITH
THIS QUOTE. SLEEP IS A BIOLOGICAL NECESSITY
,NOT A CRIME. FOR SOME PEOPLE SLEEPING
OUTSIDE IS THEIR ONLY OPTION. THE CITY OF GRANTS PASSED JAILS
AND FINES THESE PEOPLE FOR SLEEPING ANYWHERE IN PUBLIC AT
ANY TIME INCLUDING IN THEIR CARS IF THEY USE AS LITTLE AS A
BLANKET TO KEEP WARM OR A ROLLED UP SHIRT AS A PILLOW.
FOR PEOPLE WITH NO ACCESS TO SHELTER THAT PUNISHES THEM FOR
BEING HOMELESS. THAT IS UNCONSCIONABLE
AND UNCONSTITUTIONAL. SAN FRANCISCO HAS THOUSANDS OF
SHELTER BEDS SHORT. THERE ARE OVER 10,000 PEOPLE
NEEDING EXTREMELY LOW INCOME OR COMPLETELY SUBSIDIZED HOUSING.
TO CRIMINALIZE THEM IS UNCONSCIONABLE
AND UNCONSTITUTIONAL. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO DEAR PARTICIPANT
OFFICERS. I APPRECIATE THE RETURNING
SUPERVISORS INQUIRY INTO WHAT HAPPENED TO TRANSPEOPLE THIS
PRIDE WEEKEND. AND SO I PREPARE THIS COMMENT
BEFORE. THAT WAS THAT INJURY WAS
SHARED. >> I AM DEEPLY SADDENED
AND ENRAGED BY SPEEDY'S VIOLENT ,AGGRESSIVE, OUTSIZED
AND OUTSIZED ASSAULTS ON TRANS PEOPLE DURING OUR MARCH
SUPPOSEDLY OVER PAINT AND AND WHAT HAPPENED IN THE ALLEY
SUPPOSEDLY OVER PERMITS. >> AND I AM DEEPLY SADDENED
AND ENRAGED BY YOUR COMPLICITY AND SILENCE PER USUAL.
THIS IS THE BEST TRANS PEOPLE GETS.
TRANS PEOPLE ARE FLEEING THEIR STATES AND COMING HERE FOR
REFUGE. AND THIS IS THE BEST YOU HAVE
TO OFFER THEM. >> ALSO THIS COMMENT JUST KEEPS
GETTING DELETED SO LET'S SEE IF I CAN READ IT HERE OF DELETED
OFF OF THE MAYOR SOCIAL MEDIA THE MAYOR AND US APD ARE
TARGETING TRANS AND PEOPLE. >> WHY DO I SAY THAT ONE SFPD
VIOLENCE OUTSIZE ASSAULT ON THE TRANS MARCH TO THE
MAYOR SILENCE ON SAID ASSAULTS THREE AS A PD DID IT AGAIN
SATURDAY NIGHT KICKING THE STATE SENATOR OUT OF THE TRANS
MARCH MADE OUR COMMUNITY SAFER BECAUSE WE ARE NOT SAFE AROUND
A MAN WHO ABUSED HIS POWER TO TARGET AND SILENCE ANTI
GENOCIDE AND PRO PALESTINE ACTIVISM.
HE TARGETED DR. RIP AND MARIO. SORRY FOR MISPRONOUNCE HER
NAME, GOT HER FIRED FROM UCSF AND HAD TO FLEE THE COUNTRY TO
IRELAND AFTER ALL THE HATE AND HARASSMENTS AND THE SMEAR
CAMPAIGN THE STATE SENATOR DIRECTED HER WAY.
THIS IS THE SAME MAN WHO HAS ALSO BEEN TARGETING HOMELESS
POOR LGBTQ FOLKS WHO ARE OFTEN BLACK AND BROWN.
HE TARGETS POOR IMMIGRANTS WITH HIS VENDING LAWS.
HE MOURNED THE CLOSURE OF A NORDSTROM BEFORE ACKNOWLEDGING
PINK OR BROWN. THE STATE SENATOR IS CURRENTLY
MAKING BANK OFF TRANSPHOBIA LIKE EVERY OTHER TRANSPHOBE.
MEANWHILE, THE CHRONICLE HAS A PIECE ABOUT HOW WE COMPROMISED
SAN FRANCISCO'S RESPECTABILITY FOR MAGA LIKE WHY DO YOU ALL
WANT MAGGIE'S APPROVAL SO BADLY?
BUT SAN FRANCISCO S.F. GETS TO MAKE LIFE MATERIALLY AND SURELY
WORSE FOR TRANS FOLKS ABOUT ONE CRITICAL THINK PIECE IN THE
CHRONICLE OR ANY NEWS OUTLET. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS STEPHEN TORRES FROM THE CASTRO
LGBTQ CULTURAL DISTRICT TRUST ONCE AGAIN SPEAKING IN SUPPORT
OF ITEM 15 THE RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE COURSE BOYCOTT
COMMEMORATION DAY WHICH TOOK PLACE THIS PAST FRIDAY, JUNE
26TH. IT WAS A GREAT EVENT
AND ATTENDANCE BY THE SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL ALAMEDA
LABOR COUNCIL, IFP, THE TEAMSTERS IT WAS EMCEED BY OUR
DRAG LAUREATE PERSIA SUPERVISOR CHAN WAS THERE AND I THINK IT
WAS A REALLY FOR THE FOR THE CULTURAL DISTRICT IT WAS REALLY
IMPORTANT BECAUSE SOME OF THE ORGANIZERS WHICH THE HARVEY
MILK DEMOCRATIC CLUB AND AND LABOR FELT THAT IT WAS
IMPORTANT THAT LABOR WALK FROM THE CAUSE COMMEMORATION EVENT
TO THE TRANS MARCH LATER TO SHOW THAT SOLIDARITY BETWEEN
LABOR AND THE LGBTQ COMMUNITY IS STILL VITAL AND CRITICAL.
>> AND UNFORTUNATELY THE EVENTS OF THIS WEEKEND HAVE HAVE TRULY
UNDERLINED THAT THAT THIS COALITION AND THIS ALLIANCE
STILL IS CRITICAL AS WE FACE THE SAME THINGS THAT WE FACED
IN 1966 THAT WE HAVE FACED IN 1979 THAT WE FACED IN 1989
WHICH IS NEEDLESSLY ESCALATED BRUTE FORCE BY THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT AGAINST THE COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, STEVEN TORRES FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON. POLICE.
MY NAME IS DAVID. I'M HERE IN MY CAPACITY AS A
UNION STEWARD AND EXERCISING MY FIRST AMENDMENT RIGHTS AS A
SEIU 1021 UNION STEWARD FOR THE MENTAL HEALTH CHAPTER AND AS I
AGE I WANT TO RAISE AWARENESS OF AN ISSUE THAT GETS
OVERLOOKED WHEN CITY OFFICIALS EVALUATE LINE ITEMS IN THE
BUDGET TO DETERMINE WHICH PROGRAMS GET FUNDING OR NOT.
I AM TALKING ABOUT THE MISTREATMENT OF FRONTLINE STAFF
BY MIDDLE AND UPPER MANAGEMENT AND THE LACK OF ACCOUNTABILITY
FOR THEIR MISCONDUCT THAT DISTORTS PROGRAM PERFORMANCES
AND WASTES TAXPAYER MONEYS. THIS HAPPENS FREQUENTLY TO
UNION MEMBERS INCLUDING MYSELF BUT I WANT TO SHARE ONE NOTABLE
EXAMPLE MY FRIEND AND MENTOR JASON ALBERTSON, A LICENSED
CLERICAL SOCIAL WORKER WHO TRAGICALLY PASSED AWAY FROM AN
OVERDOSE LAST YEAR BECAUSE OF THE STRESSORS FOR MANAGERIAL
PURPOSES. I HEARD RUMORS FROM THOSE
IN THE FIELD THAT THE REASONS FOR JASON'S BEING STRIPPED OF
HIS CLINICAL DUTIES AND BEING ASSIGNED ADMINISTRATIVE TASKS
WERE RIDICULOUS AND CAPRICIOUS. IT COULD HAVE BEEN RESOLVED AT
THE LOWEST LEVEL BUT MANAGEMENT CHOSE NOT TO.
>> I WANT US TO REMEMBER JASON FOR MORE THAN HIS CAREER.
I WANT YOU ALL TO REMEMBER THAT WHEN MIDDLE AND UPPER
MANAGEMENT AT EPA MISTREATS THE FRONT LINE STAFF FOR ARBITRARY
ISSUES BURIED IN STAFF AND THE WEIGHT OF THE BUREAUCRACY THAT
IS THE H.R. AND NEEDLESSLY DELAYS UNION EFFORTS TO
PEACEFULLY RESOLVE LABOR ISSUES.
THEY ARE MISLEADING CITY OFFICIALS ON PROGRAM
PERFORMANCES. AND YET THESE ARE THE SAME
PEOPLE WHO ARE REPORTING PROGRAM PERFORMANCES
AND RECOMMENDING PROGRAM CUTS. I HOPE IN THE FUTURE THERE WILL
BE POLICY DISCUSSIONS BY THE BLS THAT WILL ALLOW UNION
MEMBERS TO ANNUALLY EVALUATE THEIR SUPERVISORS.
BY DOING SO THE FRONTLINE STAFF WILL KNOW THAT THEIR VOICES ARE
BEING HEARD WHEN CITY OFFICIALS EXAMINE FUTURE PROGRAM
PERFORMANCES. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
YES, WE'LL COME COLLECT THAT FROM YOU.
>> THANK YOU, DAVID, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> THANK YOU. MY NAME IS EVA CRISANTI.
I'M THE WRITER AND EDITOR AT MARIN COUNTY CONFIDENTIAL DOT
SUBSTACK DOT COM. >> AND I WOULD JUST LIKE TO
RECOGNIZE THE LAST SPEAKER'S COURAGE.
IT TAKES ENORMOUS COURAGE FOR SOMEONE TO SPEAK UP WHO IS AN
SEIU MEMBER AND I THINK YOU COULD HAVE GIVEN HIM THE GRACE
OF LOOKING AT HIM AS HE WAS SPEAKING.
>> SO I'M A LITTLE DISAPPOINTED.
I AM SPEAKING ON THE DAY OF A MOMENTOUS DECISION OF THE U.S.
SUPREME COURT THAT WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE WITHOUT THE
CASE OF WONG KIM ARK. AND I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO
NOTE THAT THAT CASE WAS BASED ON THE CHINESE EXCLUSION ACT
WHICH WAS PRODUCED OUT OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> MY MOTHER WAS BLOCKED FROM ENTRY INTO THE UNITED STATES
FOR THE ENTIRETY. MY MOM, HER TWO SISTERS AND MY
GRANDMOTHER WERE BLOCKED FROM ENTERING THE UNITED STATES FROM
JAPANESE OCCUPIED CHINA FOR THE ENTIRETY OF THE JAPANESE
OCCUPATION THAT KILLED 20 MILLION CHINESE.
WE NEVER HEAR THAT NUMBER. >> WE NOW HAVE ANOTHER MAYOR OF
SAN FRANCISCO FROM CONGREGATION EMANUEL AND AS FRED ROSENBAUM
HAS EXPLAINED IN MANY OF HIS RESEARCH BOOKS, HE'S A
PROFESSOR EMERITUS AT UC BERKELEY.
>> THE UNFORTUNATELY CONGREGATION EMANUEL PLAYED A
GREAT ROLE IN THE PASSAGE AND PROMOTION OF A GREAT DEAL
OF ANTI-ASIAN LEGISLATION. >> AND I'M VERY EXCITED THAT
MAYOR LURIE MAY BE ABLE TO ADDRESS THAT FINALLY.
LASTLY, I WOULD LIKE TO BRING YOUR ATTENTION TO YOUR ERRANT
CITY ATTORNEY WHO HAS WHOSE OFFICE HAS FAILED TO GET THE
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE COMMISSION TO COMPLY WITH MUNICIPAL CODES.
THEY HAVE BEEN ERRANT FOR NINE YEARS AND SIX MONTHS.
>> THEY FAILED TO TURN IN THE POLICE COMMISSION MINUTES TO
THE APPROPRIATE ARCHIVES AT SFO .
WELL WHY DOES THIS MATTER? IF YOU LOOK AT THE 1974
AND 1970 SIX MINUTES ESPECIALLY THE 19 76 MINUTES THANK YOU FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WE APOLOGIZE IF WE INTERRUPT
ANY SPEAKERS WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU KINDLY. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO, BOARD. GOOD TO SEE YOU AGAIN.
THE TALK AROUND US RANK AND FILE STEWARD WITH TEAMSTERS
LOCAL 853 CO-FOUNDER OF THE CRS BOYCOTT COMMEMORATION COMMITTEE
. I REALLY WANT TO THANK THE
BOARD TODAY FOR CONSIDERING THIS RESOLUTION.
THE RESOLUTION CELEBRATING THE ANNIVERSARY OF THE CRS BOYCOTT
AND PROCLAIMING JUNE 26TH, 2026 AS THE CRS BOYCOTT
COMMEMORATION DAY IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
MY BROTHER STEVEN I THINK ALREADY HIGHLIGHTED WHY THIS IS
SO IMPORTANT. JUST SPEAKING FROM THE
PERSPECTIVE OF LABOR, YOU KNOW THIS HISTORY STILL LIVES
AND BREATHES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND NORTHERN CALIFORNIA.
AND I REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR TIME ON THIS AND I'M LOOKING
FORWARD TO YOUR VOTE AND SOLIDARITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND OFFICE MAYOR OF DANIEL LARRY, THE TITLE OF MY SPEECH
TODAY IS GUMPTION SHOES TO MOMENTUM.
THE VOICE BEHIND THE MOVIE GOAT IS DONE BY STEPH CURRY.
THE THEME IS ABOUT LEAVING A LEGACY BY THINKING BIGGER.
AND THROUGH THE USE OF TEAMWORK THINKING BIG IS CERTAINLY A
GREAT INGREDIENT FOR SUCCESS. >> AND PIXAR'S CINEMATIC
ANIMATION ANSWER ON EAGLE CONCLUDED THAT NOT EVERYONE CAN
BE A GREAT ARTIST. HOWEVER, THAT ONE PERSON CAN BE
A GREAT ARTIST. HOWEVER, I CAME HERE NOT TO
SPEAK ABOUT GREATNESS. I'M HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT
TEAMWORK TEAMWORK TO ME SOUNDS LIKE A PLATITUDE.
THE WORD IN ITSELF IS A COMBINATION OF PLATYPUS
AND ATTITUDE. >> IT IS FLAT.
IT IS LIKE GOING ASKING SOMEONE GOING TO GOING FIRST DAY IS BE
YOURSELF IS BORING BUT IT'S OBVIOUSLY A FUNDAMENTAL
INGREDIENT ACHIEVE GRANDIOSE GOALS.
AND THAT'S WHY I WANT TO TELL YOU HAVE A SET OF A SKILL SET
THAT ENABLES ME TO BE A GREAT TEAM PLAYER FIRST.
I'M A MUSIC COORDINATOR FOR GLIDE.
>> I'M VERY POLARIZING ARTIST BECAUSE I COULD SING CANTONESE
NATIONAL ANTHEM AND GLIDE MEMORIAL OUT.
>> ALSO WORK AND CHASE CENTER DOING GUEST EXPERIENCE.
>> I CAN ALSO SING THE NATIONAL ANTHEM IN ENGLISH VERSION.
>> FOR THAT I WILL ISSUE AN INVITATION FOR THE BORDER
SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR TO SPEAK ON GLIDE AS WELL AS TO VISIT
THE CHASE CENTER. THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
JESSICA. HI, I'M JESSICA PASCO.
FIRST THANK YOU TO THE BOARD FOR LISTENING AND WORKING TO
RESTORE OUR FUNDING FOR EDUCATION, HEALTH CARE AND ON
HEALTH SERVICES AND MORE. >> THANK YOU.
SECOND, THE HUNTER'S POINT SHIPYARD.
THIS SUPERFUND SITE HAS A DOCUMENTED HISTORY OF FALSIFIED
SOIL TESTING BY THE NAVY'S CONTRACTOR TETRA TECH LEADING
TO A $97 MILLION FEDERAL LAWSUIT OR SETTLEMENT I'M SORRY
AND PRISON TIME FOR TWO OF US SUPERVISORS SERVED.
>> I'M ASKING FOR TRANSPARENCY ON CLEANUP SITES, INDEPENDENT
VERIFICATION OF CONTRACTOR DATA AND REAL TIME PUBLICLY
ACCESSIBLE AIR QUALITY MONITORING.
>> I'M ALSO ASKING FOR ACCOUNTABILITY FOR THE HARM
THAT WAS CAUSED AT THAT SHIPYARD, INCLUDING A DEEP
FUNDED HEALTH SURVEY AND EXPANDED SERVICES
PARTICULARLY HEALTH SERVICES FOR RESIDENTS NEARBY.
THIRD, DALIO THE HOUSING THE CITY'S HOUSING PORTAL A
DISTRICT TEN SEARCH SHOWS THAT ONLY ONE ENTRY IS IN THE
HOUSING LOTTERY FOR DISTRICT TEN.
I'M ASKING THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND ANYBODY WHO'S LISTENING IF
WE COULD ADD SOME MORE HOUSING ON TO THAT AREA FOR DISTRICT
TEN. I'M ALSO ASKING IF WE COULD
PLEASE CHANGE THE WEBSITE SO THE INCOME ELIGIBILITY ISN'T
PLAIN DOLLARS FOR EXAMPLE 0 TO $64 IS THE INCOME RANGE AND SO
OF UP TO 55% AM AND THE OTHER INCOME LEVEL.
>> FINALLY SAN FRANCISCO HAS NO SCORE OFFICE.
SMALL BUSINESS MENTORS ARE ONLY IN EAST BAY.
I'M ASKING THE BOARD TO WORK WITH SBA TO BRING ONE BACK
IDEALLY TO DISTRICT TEN AND TO ADVOCATE FOR HELP FOR OUR SMALL
BUSINESSES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, JESSICA, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND BOARD MEMBERS.
MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON. >> I COME TO TALK ABOUT THE
WORD PROGRESSIVE. THAT'S KIND OF WHY I'M WEARING
MY COAT THAT I GOT WHEN I FIRST GOT TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1964 AS
AN ADULT. PICKED UP A FEW BUTTONS ALONG
THE WAY AND LEARNED THAT BEING A PROGRESSIVE IS MORE THAN JUST
BEING OUT THERE BUT ACTUALLY MEETING WITH PEOPLE OF YOUR
COMMUNITY GETTING TOGETHER AND YES, ENJOYING THE SUN OF
SUMMER OF LOVE. >> I'M SURE YOU PROBABLY VETTED
ME. IF YOU HAVEN'T CREATED A
DOSSIER I'LL GIVE YOU A BRIEF RUNDOWN.
I'M 83 YEARS OLD. I WENT TO HASTINGS SCHOOL OF
THE LAW WHICH IS NOW IN SAN FRANCISCO.
UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA LAW. I PRACTICED IN MOSTLY FEDERAL
COURTS AND HAVE BEEN CONSCIOUSLY REPRESENTING THE
ENTREPRENEURS THE ARTISTS, THE INVENTORS AND ALL THOSE PEOPLE
THAT MADE THE WEST COAST GREAT PROGRESSIVE IS MORE THAN JUST A
WORD. AGGRESSIVE REALLY TALKS TO ALL
OF US AND I THINK THAT YOU BETTER START REALIZING
AND HERE'S WHERE IT GETS A LITTLE HOT THAT PROGRESSIVE IS
NOT THE SAME AS IN NEW YORK ONE TIME PROGRESSIVE THERE IS A
DANGER SWEEPING THE NATION WHERE PROGRESSIVE SUDDENLY
MEANS YOU HAVE TO BE SOCIALIST AND THAT'S DEFINITELY NOT THE
TRUTH. SO PLEASE WHEN YOU THINK OF
PROGRESSIVE THINK OF ALL THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN ATTRIBUTED
TO THIS CITY. >> NOT NEW YORK.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> ALL RIGHT. MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT
IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEM 15
THROUGH 19 TOGETHER IDEAS 15 THROUGH 19 WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TODAY. ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A
RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 15 THROUGH 19
TOGETHER ON ITEMS 15 THROUGH 19 SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN II MANDOLIN
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON HIGH WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I AND SUPERVISOR MAHMUD MAHMUD I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT, MR. PRESIDENT.
COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> YES. TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS.
ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDELL, MAN FOR THE LATE MRS. GLORIA DE
LA RAY. ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN
AND FOR MR. STANISLAW CHAN. >> AND I THINK THAT BRINGS US
TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK.
>> DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
WE DO NOT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
WE ARE ADJOURNED